<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aristoteles Master-piece, or, The secrets of generation displayed in all the parts thereof ...</title>
            <title>Aristotle's Masterpiece.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12246855</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12246855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56968</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 7:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aristoteles Master-piece, or, The secrets of generation displayed in all the parts thereof ...</title>
                  <title>Aristotle's Masterpiece.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 190, [13] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. How ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 53-68 missing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cushing Collection, Yale University Medical School Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Obstetrics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gynecology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reproduction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:56968:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Effigies of a Maid all Hairy, and an Infant that was black by the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of their Parents. Jovi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56968:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ARISTOTELES</hi> MASTER-PIECE, Or The Secrets of Generation diſplayed in all the parts thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Containing,</hi> 1. The Signs of Barrenneſs. 2. The way of getting a Boy or Girl. 3. Of the likeneſs of Children to Parents. 4. Of the Infuſion of the Soul into the Infant. 5. Of Monſtrous Births, and the reaſons thereof. 6. Of the benefit of Marriage to both Sexes. 7. The prejudice of unequal Matches. 8. The diſcovery of Inſufficiency. 9. The cauſe and cure of the Green-ſickneſs. 10. A Diſcourſe of Maiden-heads. 11. How a Midwife ought to be qualified. 12. Directions and Cautions to Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes. 13. Of the Privities. 14. The Fabrick of the Womb. 15. The Uſe and Action of the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals. 16. Signs of Conception, and whether of a Male or Female. 17. To diſcover falſe Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. 18. Inſtructions for Women with Child. 19. For preventing Miſcarriage. 20. For Women in Child-bed. 21. Of ordering new-born Infants, and many other very uſeful Particulars. To which is added a word of Advice to both Sexes in the Act of Copulation: And the Pictures of ſeveral Monſterous Births drawn to the Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Entered According to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. How,</hi> and are to be ſold next door to the Anchor Tavern in Swee-things-Rents in Cornhil. 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56968:2"/>
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>IT plainly appears in Holy Writ, that this glorious Univerſe, beſpangled with gaudy Fires, and every where adorned with wonderful Objects, proclaming the Wiſdom and <hi>Omnipotence</hi> of the great Work-Maſter, who in ſix days erected all things for his pleaſure, was at firſt drawn out of nothing, or at moſt a formleſs Chaos of Confuſion, a diſordered and confounded heap of jarring Elements toſs'd and jumbl'd together, under the diſmal ſhades of during Night, eldeſt of things; no Fruitfulneſs nor Pleaſure, no Creature that had breath had being in the place this lower World poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes, till God out of the abundance of his Goodneſs ſent forth his Holy Spirit, who dove-like, with mighty out-ſpread Wings, ſat brooding on the vaſt Abyſs, and made it pregnant: then Light put Darkneſs ſoon to flight, and all the glorious Lamps of Heaven appeared, all Creatures ſoon had being, and every Plant, Tree, Herb, or Flower of fragrant ſmell ſprung from the Vernant Earth, raiſed by command above the Waters, every thing of uſe having Seed in it ſelf, that no ſecond Creation needed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56968:3"/>not, but ſtill the Lordly Creature who ſhould rule the Creatures being wanting, he was framed more Glorious than all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as not made without mature Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Deliberation, and ſtamped in the divine Similitude, inſpired with the infuſed breath of Life, beyond what any other Creature durſt to boaſt. The contemplating of which, long ſince made the <hi>Royal Pſalmiſt</hi> break out into this Rapture, <hi>viz. What is Man that thou art mindful of him, and the Son of Man that thou viſiteſt him? Thou madeſt him lower than the Angels: To Crown him with Glory and Worſhip. Thou makeſt him to have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Works of thy Hands: and thou haſt put all things in ſubjection under hhis Feet.</hi> Pſal. 8. ver. 4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p>Thus, I ſay, when God had created the World, and furniſhed it with whatſoever ſeemed good in his ſight, and that there was nothing wanting for neceſſary uſe, commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity and pleaſure, it ſeemed good to him then, to make one that might uſe them to his Glory, and take delight in rejoycing in them; wherefore when Natures Ornaments were all compleat, he brought Man into the World as into his own Poſſeſſion; and that he might not be diſconſolate, nor ſolitary, gave him a Woman for a Helper &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, infuſing into them a force of love
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56968:3"/>and deſire towards each other. And of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creating their likeneſs, having prepared for that purpoſe a ſwelling Humor or Spirit, and Organical parts, and that the one thro' fear or neglect, ſhould not be induced to decline the Society of the other, he added Allurements, and deſire of mutual embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that ſo they might in procreation be ſweetly affected, and pacified by wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ways, for unleſs this was natural to all kind of Creatures, they would be regardleſs of Poſterity, and procreation would ceaſe, whereby mankind would quickly be loſt, and the Affairs of mortals of no durance. But that this paſſiouate deſire might ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opporate, as well in ſenſual felicity as on the imagination. God has firmly impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it in all Creatures ſubject thereto, both Male and Female, but more eſpecially on man, and leaſt it ſhould prove unruly in him and not eaſily ſubdued: he has thought it convenient to preſcribe him bounds, in granting him the uſe of the Matrimonial Bed, that ſo they might not defile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with wandridg luſt, who want the Gift of Continency, wherefore ſo ſoon as Copulation is finiſhed, and the Woman happens to prove with Child, great is Natures cunning in foſtering, coagulating and framing the Seed of both Sex, that at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56968:4"/>the ſet time when nine months are run over Man that ruler and ornament of the ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary World may come forth: In Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to which my ſtry of Generation Holy <hi>Job</hi> in the tenth Chapter of his Book thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelf, <hi>viz. Haſt thou not powred me out as Milk, and curdled me like Cheeſe? Thou haſt cloathed me with Skin and Fleſh, and haſt fenced me with Bones and Sinewes. Thou haſt granted me life, and favour, and thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation hath preſerved my Spirit.</hi> But not to be tedious in prolonging on this Subject, I ſhall proceed to unravel the myſtrey of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and divers other Myſteries? as I well hope to the fatisfaction of the learned and ingenious of the Age, whoſe diſcretion, paſt doubt, will wreſt it to no other end than to what it was deſigned; <hi>viz.</hi> for the benefit and advantage of the modeſty of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sex; I not deſiring this Book ſhould fall into the hands of any obſeene Perſon, whoſe Folly or Malice may turn that into Ridicule that loudly proclaims the infinite Wiſdom of an <hi>omnipotent</hi> Creator, who by his mighty working is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf.</p>
               <closer>Gloria Deo in Excelſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56968:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER I.</hi> Of Marriage, and at what Age Virgins and Youths are capable of Generation, and the reaſon that prompts them to deſire Copulation; with the ſigns of Barrenneſs, and how long a Man or Woman are capable of getting Children.</head>
               <p>THat Marriage is an Honourable State ordained by God in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and ſince confirmed by our bleſſed Saviour, who wrought his firſt Miracle at a Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I hope none will deny; therefore it is convenient that Parents well take care of their Daughters Chaſtity, and when they find them inclinable to Marriage, not rigorouſly to reſtrain their Affections, for Nature will have its courſe, but rather to provide for them, if poſſible, ſuch Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands as may be for their advantage, and with whom they may live comfortably in that bleſſed State, leſt being croſſed in their purpoſes, and delayed, they part with their Honour diſhonourable ways.</p>
               <p>The propenſion and inclination of Maids to Marriage, is to be diſcovered by many Symptoms; as, when Nature fringes the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56968:5"/>obſcure parts, and their Terms flow at the time appointed, which is uſually in the Fourteenth or Fifteenth Year of their Age, when as the Seed increaſeth in ſome ſooner, and in others later, according to their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits or Conſtitutions: And the Blood, which is no longer taken to augment their Bodies, abounding, incites their Minds and Imaginations to Venery. And by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Seed, many times it falls out that they are cruelly afflicted with fainting Fits, and ſtrangling of the Mother: for all learned Phyſicians are of Opinion, that more harm comes by the Seed corrupting, than by their Courſes being unſeaſonably obſtructed; for the Seed derogates to a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous quality; and from the effects thereof ariſe the Swarth and weaſel Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour in Maids, when they begin to be in Love, and deſirous of Copulation; as alſo their ſhort Breathings, Tremblings, and Pantings of the Heart. The Expulſive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties being moved to caſt out the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Humour. But if they happen to be Married to their own Content, theſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions vaniſh, and their native Beauty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns more gay than before: nor is their eager gazing, &amp; deſiring to aſſociate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Men, a leſſer ſign that Nature prompts them to deſire what ſhe ordain'd:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56968:5"/>Their due of which, ſometimes being by obdurate Parents debarred in a lawful way, breaking the bounds of modeſty, rather than enduring ſuch violent Agitations and Conflicts within themſelves, they ſatiate their deſire in unlawful Love. The ſame may in all Particulars be obſerved in young brisk Widows, whom Death, that Enemy of ſweet Conjugal Love, has ſeparated from the Boſom of their Husbands.</p>
               <p>At fourteen Years of Age, commonly the Terms in Virgins begins to flow, and then they are capable of Conceiving, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue generally till forty four; at what time, for the moſt part, the Eflux being ſtayed, they are no longer capable of Generation, unleſs ſuch as are exceeding healthful, ſtrong of body, and have uſed themſelves to Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, who have appear'd to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Children till fifty five Years; but ſuch Prodigies rarely happen, although the Terms extend ſarther in ſome Women than in others; but many times ſuch Eflux proceeds not from any natural cauſe, but by reaſon of ſome violent ſtraining, or other violence, and does often endanger the life of the Party: And therefore young Men that marry Women ſurmounting the Age aforeſaid, if they expect Children, unleſs by Miracle, muſt labour againſt the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56968:6"/>Wind, though if an old Man, that is not worn out by Diſeaſes and Incontinency, marry a brisk lively Laſs, there is hopes even to threeſcore and ten, and ſome that are extraordinary luſty, till fourſcore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> that Famous and Learned Phyſician, is of Opinion, that a Youth at 16 years, or between that and 17, having much vital ſtrength, may be capable of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Children, and that force and heat of Procreating matter continually increaſes till 45, 50, &amp; 65. and at the end of the latter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to flagg; the Seed by little and little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming unfruitful, the natural Spirits being extinguiſhed, and the humours dried up; and in general, moſt Phyſicians at this day do obſerve it, but as to particulars, as I have before mentioned, it often happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth otherwiſe; nay, 'tis reported by a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Author, that in the Reign of <hi>Erecus,</hi> King of <hi>Sweedland,</hi> a Man was married at a Hundred years old, to a Bride of Thirty, and had many Children by her, but look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo freſh, that ſuch as knew him not took him not to exceed half that Age.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Campania,</hi> where the Air is tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſerene, and calm, men of 80 years uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally marry young Virgins, and have Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by them, which argues, that Age in men hinders not Procreation, unleſs they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56968:6"/>be exhauſted in their Youth, and their Members ſhriveled up. If any ask why a Women is ſooner barren than a Man? I anſwer, the Cauſe is, the natural Heat, which is more predominant in the latter than in the former; for ſince a Woman is more moiſt than a Man, as her Courſes do moſt evidently demonſtrate, as alſo the ſoftneſs of her Body; 'tis alſo apparent, that he doth exceed her in Native heat; and as for that heat, it is the chief thing that concocts the Humours, and changes them into the ſubſtance of the Seed, which Aliment the Woman wanting, grows fat, when a Man, by reaſon of that heat, melts his fat by degrees, and his Humours are diſſolved, but by the benefit thereof they are elaborated into Seed: and this may, for the better Confirmation of what I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe be added, That the Woman is not ſo ſtrong as a Man, nor ſo wiſe and prudent, nor hath ſo much reaſon, nor is ſo ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in contriving her Affairs, whereby the Faculties are hindered in their operation. And ſo I conclude my Aſſertion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56968:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> General and particular Rules, laid down by Learned Phyſicians, how to proceed in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Male or Female Child; and of the <hi>Embrio</hi> and perfect Birth, and the Seaſon ſitteſt for Copulation.</head>
               <p>WHen a young likely <hi>Couple</hi> have entred the holy State of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, &amp; are deſirous of mutual enjoyment for Generation ſake, which is the chief end for which Wedlock was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, and rather covet to be bleſſed with one Sex than another, let them know firſt for certain, that the Succeſs of ſuch things depends upon Divine Providence, tho' ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary cauſes muſt be actual and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental therein; and thoſe are eſpecially two: Firſt, the Genital Humour which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds partly from the Brain, and partly from the Liver, the Fountain of Blood; then the ſpirit that is conveyed by Arteries from the Heart, by force whereof the Yard is erected, and made capable to eject the Seed; and partly it flows from the whole Body without exception. To which may be added the Appetite and deſire to Copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56968:7"/>which fires the Imagination with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual Fancies, or by the ſight and feeling a brisk charming Beauty, whoſe wit and livelineſs may much incite, and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the Courage; but if Nature be infee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, then are there fit artificial Remedies to reſtore it; <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch meats as moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the affording ſuch aliment as proves to make Seed abound, and reſtore the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caies of Nature, that the Faculties may free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opporate: for as Dung and well manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring reſtores Ground that is worn out and heartleſs; even ſo ſeaſonable and proper Diet opporates to the reſtoring the faint heart, weak ſpirit, coldneſs and dryneſs of the Genital Parts, and reduceth the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Nerves to their Temperament, and removes Impediments, obſtructing the Procreation of Children. Then ſince the Diet may, and will alter the evil ſtate of the Body to a better, it is neceſſary that ſuch as are ſubject to Barrenneſs ſhould eat ſuch meat only as tend to render them fruitful; and among ſuch things as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing and ſtirring up thereto, are all meats of good juice, that nouriſh well, and makes the body lively and full of ſap: of which Faculty are all hot moiſt meats: for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Gallen,</hi> the ſubſtance of Seed is made of the pure concocted and windy ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56968:8"/>of Blood, from whence we may conclude there is in many things a power to accumulate or heap up Seed, as alſo to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it, and other things of force to cauſe Erection and Ejection of Humour, as Hen-Eggs, Pheaſants, Woodcocks, Guatſappers, Thruſhes, Black birds, young Pidgeons, Sparrows, Partridge, Capons, Almones, Pine-nuts, Raſons, Currants, all ſtrong Wines moderately taken, eſpecially thoſe made of the Grapes of <hi>Italy;</hi> but the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals are chiefly erected and provoked by <hi>Satyrium, Eringoes, Creſſes, Ereſſimum.</hi> Parſnips, Artichokes, Turnips, Rapes, Aſparagus, Candid Ginger, Gallinga, Acorns bruiſed to powder and drunk in Muſcadel, Scalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Sea-ſhell Fiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And theſe, though excellent Reſtoratives, will not have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Operation, but you muſt uſe your ſelf to them ſometime before you handle your Arms, or your Wife will grudg the charge; for when Husbands will win their Wives favour, then they ſhall account nothing too good nor too dear for them: then muſt they be well prepared to enter this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict; and when they find themſelves ſo to be, they muſt take the opportunity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their buſineſs well, and that is when the monthly Terms are over, leſt the Seed be hindred from coagulating and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56968:8"/>and the Womb be rendred unfit for Conception. When therefore the Terms are finiſhed, and the Womb well cleanſed, they muſt proceed decently, and not over raſhly, tho' courage and activity muſt not be wanting, nor the force of Imagination: and having performed what is neceſſary, the Woman muſt gently repoſe on her right ſide, with her head lying low, and her body ſinking down, that by ſleeping in that Poſture the cells on the right ſide of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix may prove the receptacles of the Seed, in which are the greateſt force of Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive heat, which is the chief inducement to the procreation of Male Children, and rarely miſſes to anſwer the expectation of ſuch as experience it, eſpecially if they keep themſelves warm, and without much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, leaning for the moſt part to the right and drinking a little Spirit of Saffron and Juyce of Hyſop in a Glaſs of <hi>Malligo</hi> or <hi>Aligant</hi> when they lie down and riſe, for the ſpace of a Week. Now the fitteſt time for the Procreation of Male Children, is when the Sun is in <hi>Leo,</hi> and the Moons Sign is <hi>Virgo, Scorpio,</hi> or <hi>Sagitarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Order may be obſerved for a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Child, by lying as aforeſaid, on the left-ſide, and ſtrongly ſancying a Female in the time of Procreation, eſpecially if the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56968:9"/>Woman drink the decoction of Female <hi>Mercury,</hi> four days from the firſt day of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; the Male <hi>Mercury</hi> (both Herbs ſo called,) having the like Operation in caſe of a Male Child, for the juyce or concoction of theſe Simples are of force, the one to purge the right, and the other the left ſide of the Womb, and thereby open the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles, making a way for the Semenary of Generation: and the beſt time to copulate for this Sex, is, when the Moon is in the Wain and the Sign in <hi>Libra,</hi> or <hi>Aquarius;</hi> for then they will be of a moſt gentle, affable temper, very fair and perfect in all their Members. <hi>Avicenna,</hi> an Author of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, deſcribes the time of Procreation thus: When, ſaith he, the Terms are ſpent and the Womb is cleanſed, which is commonly in five days, or ſeven at moſt, if a Man lye with his Wife from the firſt day ſhe is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the fifth, ſhe will conceive a Male, but from the fifth to the eighth day a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, and from the eighth to the twelfth a Male again; but after that number of days peradventure neither diſtinctly, but both in an <hi>Hermophrodite.</hi> And thus this Opinion of his by the Learned is explained; <hi>viz.</hi> for as much as the firſt day the Wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing cleanſed, and the ſordid humour perfectly purged forth, the Matrix has more heat,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56968:9"/>whereby the Seed of either Sex are better contracted, and take ſurer place on the right-ſide of the Womb, by the attracting force of the Liver and right Kidney, from which alſo in thoſe days het Blood is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the <hi>Nutriment</hi> of the Child that ſhall be for the left part, as being cold, numb'd and void of Blood cannot contribute any thing ſo ſoon as the Terms are purged, but Blood is drawn later, and more ſparingly from the Veins on the left ſide, which are called emulgent Veins, that creep about the Milt and left Kidney; ſo that at length, after the firſt day until the eighth day, ſome Blood comes forth of them, whereby the Child is to be nouriſh'd ſo that when theſe Parts perform their Office, and the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide ceaſes by reaſon of the Situation and cold <hi>Nutriment,</hi> a Female is generated: after the eighth day the parts on the right ſide opporate again, &amp; Blood comes from them to nouriſh the Male after theſe circuit of days, becauſe the menſtrual Blood flows without diſtinction from all parts, and the Matrix is made too moiſt with cold Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors flowing into it; and the Seed adheres to neither ſide, but floats in the middle of the Womb, the Seed of either Sex confounded or confuſed, and out of due Place and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, fixed at laſt in the Cell at the bottom
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56968:10"/>of the Womb, generates an <hi>Hermophrodite,</hi> tho' ſometimes ſuch unuſual and unuatural Conceptions are occaſioned by the indecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Copulation, when prepoſterouſly the Woman in the Act lies uppermoſt, and the Man under her, or by the force of ſtrange Imaginations: but many are of Opinion ſuch Births happen through the powerful influence of <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In a word, they that would be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for their Wedlock Actions, and be happy in the fruit of their labour, muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to copulate at diſtance of time, not too often nor yet too ſeldom, for both theſe hurt Fruitfulneſs alike; for to eject immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately weakens a Man and waſts his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and too often cauſes the Seed, by long continuance, to be ineffectual, and not manly enough. And thus much for the firſt general and particular; from whence I ſhall proceed to the ſecond; which is, to give the Reader to underſtand how the Child is formed in the Womb, and what Accidents it is incident to, how nouriſhed, and when brought forth.</p>
               <p>Certain it is, there are various Opinions concerning this matter; therefore I ſhall, for the ſatisfaction of the curious, lay down the Opinions of the learned, as thus. Man conſiſts of the Seed of both united in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56968:10"/>Matrix by Copulation, and for the firſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven days the Mothers Blood running to it it grows in ſhape like an Egg; but there is a forming faculty and virtue in the Seed from a divine and heavenly gift, it being abundantly indued with Vital and Etherial Spirit, which gives ſhape and form to the Child; ſo that all the parts and bulk of the Body, which is made up in the ſpace of many months, and is by degrees framed and formed into a decent and comely Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of a Man, do conſiſt in that, and are adumbrated thereby: on which Holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> contemplating, fell into his divine Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Admiration expreſſed in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138. <hi>I will praiſe thee, O Lord, becauſe I am wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made: thy Works are wonderful. Mr Soul ſearcheth and knoweth it right. Well thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt all my Bones when I was faſhinned in the ſecret place, and when I was wonderfully formed in my Mothers Womb. Thy Eyes beheld me yet unmade, and in thy Book were all my Members written, which day by day were faſhioned. Thy Knowledge is wonderful unto me, whereby I was made, I cannot underſtand it.</hi> &amp;c. And Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians that have narrowly contemplated Mans Nature, conſtitute four different times wherein this Microcoſm or little World is framed and perfected in the Womb.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56968:11"/>
               <p>Firſt, When after Copulation and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual embracing it hath the nature of Seed; at which time it is called Conception or Geniture, becauſe the Seeds of the Man and Woman mixing and fermenting, become like Cream and are perfect in the firſt week if no Eflux happen, which ſometimes falls out through the ſlipperineſs of the Matrix, or the head thereof that ſhuts over like a Roſe bud opening on a ſudden by reaſon of ſome cold diſtemper, or over-wearineſs in Travel.</p>
               <p>The ſecond time of forming is conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when Nature and the force of the Womb, by the uſe of her own inbred for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and vertue, makes a manifeſt mutation in the Seed, ſo that all the ſubſtance ſeems congealed Fleſh and Blood, rather than Seed, which happens about the 12 or 14 day after Copulation; and though this Concretion, or fleſhy Maſs, abound with hot fiery blood, yet it remains undiſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able without form of figure, and may be called the rough draught, or <hi>Embrio,</hi> and well likened to Seed which is ſown in the ground, which through kindly heat and moiſture grows up by degrees into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect form, either in Plant or Grain; or as when a Potter faſhions a Veſſel out of a rude Lump of Clay.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56968:11"/>
               <p>The third time to make up this Fabrick, is ſet when the three principal Parts ſhew themſelves evidently and perſpicuouſly, <hi>viz.</hi> The Heat from whence proceeds the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, the Brain from which the Nerves proceed like many ſmall threads running through the whole Body, and the Liver from whence the Veins derive their Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Theſe are the Seeds and Fountains of Life, that nouriſh and ſupport each part of the Body; in framing which, the Faculty of the Womb is buſied from the time of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to the eighteenth day of the firſt Month.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, which time reacheth to the 28 or 30 day, the outward Parts are ſeen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely claborated and diſtinguiſhed by Joynts, and then the Child begins to grow and pant; from which Progreſs of days, by reaſon the Limbs are divided, and the whole frame is perfect, it is no longer held an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Child or <hi>Embrio,</hi> that is, a Concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſprings ſorth, but is held to be a perfect and abſolute Child. Males for the moſt part are perfect by the 30 day, but Females ſeldom till the 42 or 45 day; and the reaſon why the one is ſooner perfected than the other, is, that the heat of the Womb is greater in producing the Male than the Female; for heat extends the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56968:12"/>like ſoft wax, diffuſing &amp; delating it, and hen by its force contracting, framing and faſhioning it, ſo heat and vigout of the Body, and Alacrity of nature in the Man makes the Male to move in 3 months, but the Female rarely under 4, at which time alſo his Hair and Nailes come forth, and the Child begins to ſtir, kick, and tumble in the Womb; ſo that the motion is plainly perceived, and the Women are troubled with nauſeating and loathing of their meat, and oftentimes covet and greedily long for things contrary to Nutriment, as Coals, Rubliſh, Chalk, Lime, Starch, Oat-meal, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw Fleſh and Fiſh or the like, which deſire proceeds from a former contraction of evil humours, occaſioning im pure Blood in their containing Veſſel, within, and often occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions abortion and miſcarriage; ſome Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as it has been noted by divers Authors of Credit, have been ſo extravegant in their longings, that they have coveted <hi>Hob-Nails, Leather, Herſe Fleſh, Mans Fleſh,</hi> and the Fleſh of divers ravenous Be aſts, for want of which they have caſt their <hi>Birth</hi> untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or the Child has contiued dead in the Womb, for many days, to the eminent hazard of the Womans life: But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this great myſtery, I ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold by what means the Infant is ſuſtained
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56968:12"/>in the Womb, and the poſture it there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in.</p>
               <p>The Infant being arrived to ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, is faſtened by a long ſtring to the Navel, as the Apple by the ſtalk is faſtened to the Tree; by which, through the help of the Umbelical Vein, it is nouriſhed by a Fountain of pure Blood, not taking it in at the mouth, as ſome ignorant People have imagined; that being of no uſe during the aboad in the Womb, neither do any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements fall from the Veſſels of Evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but the Umbelical Vein ſpringing from the Matrix, enters the Liver in two parts, &amp; terminates in <hi>Vena Porta,</hi> from which the moſt pure Blood from the Seminary Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are derived to the Matrix. And hende it is that the Blood and Spirits, like Auxiliaries, are always convey'd downwards, that ſo none of them be wanting, whereof are thoſe Channels and Rivers of Veins and Arteries that proceed from the Mothers Body are carried to the Womb, and then faſtened into the Navel, feed the Child by inſenſible ways, and by the faculty of the Seed that is foſtered by the heat of the Womb, and moiſtened with Blood; being perfected at the times ſpecified in all its parts equal ballanced, it is in the midſt of the Womb, as in the Center lying all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56968:13"/>on a heap, and being ſomething long, is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned round, ſo that the Head a little inclines, and it lays its Chin on its Breaſt, his Heels and Ancles upon his Buttocks, its Hands on its Cheeks, and its Thumbs to its Eyes; but its Legs and Thighs are carried upward with its Hams bending, ſo that they touch the bottom of its belly: the former and that part of the body which is over againſt us, as the Fore-head, Noſe, Face, are turned towards the Mothers Back, and the Head inclining downwards towards the Cocyx or Rump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone that joyns to the <hi>Os Sacrum,</hi> which Bone, together with <hi>Os Pubis,</hi> in the time of the Birth parts and is looſened; whence it is that Male Children commonly come with their Faces downwards, or with their Heads turned ſomewhat <hi>Oblique,</hi> that their Faces may be ſeen; but the Female chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with their Faces upward, tho' ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it happens that Births follow not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Natures order, but Children come forth with their feet ſtradling, their Necks bowed, and their Heads lying <hi>Oblique</hi> with their Hands ſtretch'd out, which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endangers themſelves and the Mother, giving the Midwife great trouble to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them nto the World: but when all things proceed orderly and naturally, the Child, when Natures ſet bounds are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56968:13"/>is deſirous to break its bounds, and come forth of the Womb; and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining himſelf, he rowls downward; for he cannot longer be obſcured in thoſe hiding places, than he can find Nutriment from the Navel, and the heat of the Heart can ſubſiſt without external reſpiration; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being grown great, he is more and more deſirous of Nutriment and Light; when coveting the Etherial Air, he by ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to obtain it breaks the membrains and Coverings whereby he was reſtrained and fenced againſt Attrition; and for the moſt part with bitter Pangs of the Mother iſſucth forth to view the Day, commonly in the ninth Month; for then the Matrix divided, and <hi>Oſs Pubis</hi> being looſened, the Woman ſtrives what ſhe can to caſt forth her bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and the Child doing the like to get forth by the help of its inbred ſtrength, the Birth comes to be perfect; but if the Child be dead, then more dangerous is the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, tho' Nature, as a kind Commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, often helpeth the Womans weakneſs herein; but the Child that is quick and lively labours no leſs than the Woman.</p>
               <p>Now there are Bitths at 7 or 8 months, and ſome Women go to the <hi>10th</hi> month; but of theſe, and the Reaſons for them, I ſhall ſpeak more largely in another place, and at preſent proceed to unrayel other my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56968:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Reaſon why Children are often like their Parents, and what the Mathers Imagination contributes thereto: How the Mother contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes Seed, and is a Companion in the whole Generation; and whence grows the Kind, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the Man or the Woman is the cauſe of the Male or Female Child, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is the opinion of learned Phyſicians, grounded upon reaſon, That if a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the Act of Copulation afford moſt Seed, her likeneſs will have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er impreſſion upon the Child; but if on the contrary, then will follow the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry effects; or if a proportionable quantity proceed from either, then will the Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude depend upon either.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> is of opinion, That when a Mans ſeed falls on the left ſide of the womb a Male Child may be gotten: but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it is the proper place for a Female, there will be ſomething in it greatly reſembling a Woman, <hi>viz.</hi> It will be fairer, whiter, and ſmoother, not very ſubject to have hair on the Body or Clain, long lank hair on the Head, the Voice ſmall and ſharp,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56968:14"/>and the Courage feeble; and arguing yet further, he ſays, that a Female may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance be procreated if the Seed fall on the right ſide; but then through extraordinary heat, ſhe will be very large boned, full of Courage, indued with a big Voice, and have her Chin and boſom hairy not being ſo clear as others of the Sex; ſubject to quarrel with her Husband when married, for the ſuperiority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet in caſe of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, nothing is more powerful than the imagination of the Mother; for if ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in her mind, or do by chance faſten her eyes upon any Object, and imprint it in her Memory, the Child in its out ward parts frequently has ſome repreſentation thereof; ſo whilſt a Man and Woman are in the Act of Copulation, if the Woman earneſtly behold his Countenance and fix her mind thereon, without all peradventure, the Child will reſemble the Father; nay ſo powerful is its Operation, that though a Woman be in unlawful Copulation, yet if fear or any thing elſe cauſes her to fix her mind upon her Husband, the Child will reſemble him, tho' he never got it. The ſame effect, according to the opinion of the Learned, proceeds from Imagination in cauſe of Warts, Moldſpots, Stains, Daſhes, and the figures of ſtrange things, though
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56968:15"/>indeed they ſometimes happen thro' frights or extravagant longings. Many Women there are, that ſeeing a Hare croſs them when great with Child, will, through the ſtrength of imagination, bring forth a Child with a hairy-lip. Some Children again are born with flat Noſes, wry Mouths, great bluber Lips, and ill ſhaped Bodies, and moſt aſcribe the reaſon to the ſtrange conceit of the Mother, who has buſied her Eyes and Mind upon ſome ill ſhaped or diſtorted Creature; therefore it greatly behoves all Women with Child to avoid any mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ſight, or at leaſt to have a ſtedfaſt mind, not eaſily fixed upon any one thing more than another. And this opinion <hi>Pliny</hi> confirms in his <hi>7th</hi> Book of natural things, and the <hi>12th</hi> Chapter. The Famour Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas More</hi> likewiſe confirms it, and diſcants merrily on a Paſſage of his times, wherein a Perſon having divers Children, would own none but one that was like him, when in the end it proved, by the aſſeveration of the Mother, that all, except that, were of his own begetting; but whilſt another man was mounted in his Saddle, ſhe fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he would come and detect her in the Act, had her imagination ſo fix'd on him, that as ſhe conceived, the ſimilitude could proceed from no other cauſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56968:15"/>it is apparent that likeneſs can confiirm no Child to be a lawful Fathers own: yet in manners, wit, and the propenſion of the mind, daily examples reach us that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which have all force and Spirits from the faculty of the Seed, are commonly of the ſame condition with their progenitors, and of the ſame nature, but there is much in this, whether venery be uſed with great or weak deſire, for many are leſs venerous and not ſo hot, and conſequeutly not ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of copulation, but rather decline it, unleſs the obſtreporuſneſs of their Wives cauſe them to complyance therein, and then they proceed faintly and drowſily, whence it happens that the Children fall ſhort of the Parents nature, wit and manners; and hence it is that wiſe men frequently beget ſtupid ſloathful Children of feeble minds, becauſe they are not much given to theſe delights, but as I ſaid on the contrary, when the Progenitors are hot in venerious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and do liberally and abundantly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves therein: it oftentimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that the Children are of the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, manners and actions of the mind with their Parents. And thus much for the firſt point, now I ſhall proceed to the Second, which is to prove that the mother's equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contributing to the making the Child, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56968:16"/>
               <p>Though it is apparent that the Seed of man is the chief efficient and beginning of action, motion, and Generation, yet that the Woman does afford ſeed, and effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contributes in that particular to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation of the Child, is evinced by ſtrong reaſons; in the firſt place, Seminary Veſſels had been given them in vain, and genital Teſticles inverted, if the Woman wanted Seminal exceſſence; for being Nature doth nothing in vain, therefore it muſt be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they were made for the uſe of ſeed and procreation and fixed in their proper places, both the Teſtacles and Receptacles of Seed, whoſe nature and force is to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and afford fruitful vertue to the Seed: and to prove this, there needs no ſtronger Argument than that if a Woman do not uſe Copulation to eject her Seed, ſhe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falls into ſtrange Diſeaſes, as appears by young Widows and Virgins. A ſecond reaſon may be urged, that although the ſociety of a lawful Bed conſiſt not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in theſe things, yet it is apparent, that the Female Sex is not better won, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more blith and jocund, than when they are often ſatisfied this way; which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to believe that they have greater pleaſure, and reccive more content than a man: for ſince by Nature much delight
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56968:16"/>accompanies the ejection of the Seed, by breaking forth of the ſwelling Spirit, and the ſtiffneſs of the Nerves, in which caſe the operation of the Womans part is double, ſhe ſuffering both ways, even by ejection and reception, whereby ſhe is more recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and delighted in the Venereal Act.</p>
               <p>Hence it is that the Child more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſembles the Mother than the Father, becauſe the Mother confers the moſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its Generation: and further it may be inſtanced from the great love they bear them, for beſides their contributing Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal matter, they, during the time they are in the Womb, feed and nouriſh the Child with the pureſt Fountain of Blood: which Opinion <hi>Galen</hi> confirms, by allowing the Child to participate more of the Mother than the Father, and refers the difference of the Sex to the influence of menſtrual Blood; but the reaſon of the likeneſs he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to the force of the Seed; for as Plants receive more from fruitful ground than from the induſtry of the Husbandman, ſo the Infant in more abundance receives from the Mother than the Father; for firſt the Seed of both is heaped and foſtered in the Womb, and there grows to perfection, being nouriſhed with blood. And hence it is that Children for the moſt part affect
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56968:17"/>their Mothers beſt, for it proceeds from the nearneſs of nature by a natural inſtinct, becauſe the Mothers forces were moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about 'em? for nine months, and ſometimes ten, ſhe nouriſheth the Child with her pureſt Blood, then her love towards it newly born, and the likelyneſs do clearly demonſtrate, that the Woman affordeth Seed, and that Women do contribute more towards making the Child than Men. And thus much for the clearing of this point alſo: and now to the third thing propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> Whence grows the kind, and whether the Man or the Woman is the cauſe of the Male or Female Inſant.</p>
               <p>The primal cauſe, as is juſtly due in this and all other cauſes, we muſt aſcribe to God the Ruler and Diſpoſer of all things; yet many things, by his high ſufferance, proceed in regular order by the Rules of Nature, and are carried by their inbred motion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their uſual and natural Courſe without variation, tho' indeed by favour from on high. <hi>Sarah</hi> conceived <hi>Iſaac; Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Samuel;</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt;</hi> but theſe were to fulfil the Almighties Decree: nor ſince thoſe times have the Prayers of the righteous been unſucceſsful, in obtaining Children: but paſſing over ſuch Supernatural and Extraordinary cauſes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56968:17"/>that have their peculiar effects: I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſpeak of things natural and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and how Nature worketh by her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Forces; for ſhe prepares a Body fit for the reception of the Soul (of whoſe Nature I ſhall hereaſter diſcourſe) and gives every thing its temper; but ſiuce there are two Principals out of which the Body of Man is made, and which render the Child like the Progenitors, and to be of one or the other Sex, <hi>viz.</hi> Seed common to both Sex, as I have before demonſtrated, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrual Blood proper to the Woman only. The Similitude conſiſts in the force of the Male or Female Seed, ſo that it proves like to the one or the other, as more or leſs plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is afforded by either; but the difference of Sex is not referred to the Seed, but to the menſtrual Blood, which is proper to the Woman; for were that force altogether retained in the Seed, the mans Seed being of a hotter quality than the Womans, Male Children would be ſuperabundant, &amp; none of the other Sex (or very rarely) would be propagated, whereof the kind of the Creature is attributed to the temperament of the active qualities, which conſiſt in heat and cold, and to the ſubſtance or nature of the matter under them, that is to the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the menſtrual Blood: now the Seed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56968:18"/>affords both force to procreate and form the Child, and matter for its Generation, alſo in the menſtrual Blood there is both matter and force; for as the Seed muſt helps the material Principles, ſo likewiſe the menſtrual Blood, the potential Seed, is, ſaith famous <hi>Galen,</hi> Blood well concocted by the Veſſels that contain it, ſo that Blood is not only the matter of generating the Child, but alſo Seed, in poſſibility that menſtrual Blood has both principles, as matter, and faculty of effecting. Many do allow that the Seed is the ſtrongeſt efficient, the matter of it being very little in quantity, but the potential of efficient faculty of it is very feeble: wherefore, if the material part and principal of Generation, according to which the Sex is made, were only in the menſtrual Blood, then would the Children be all or moſtly Females, as if the efficient force was in the Seed, they would be all Males: but ſince both have operation in menſtrual Blood, Matter predominates in quantity, and in the Seed force and verue. Deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaith ſamous <hi>Galen,</hi> the Child receives its Sex rather from the Mother than from the Father, although his Seed doth contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſomething to the material Principles, though more weakly. But as for ſimilitude, although Imagination be of extraordinary
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56968:18"/>force, it is referr'd rather to the Father than the Mother, as to the quality of the Seed, at or for a ſhort time after Copulation, but continues not long ſo to do, for the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Seed receiving faculty from the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrual Blood for the ſpace of nine months, overpowers the Mans as to that particular, becauſe the menſtrual Blood flowing into the Veſſels, rather cheriſhes and augments the one than the other; from which it may be more eaſily conjectured, that the Woman not only affords matter to make the Child, but force and vertue to perfect the Conception, though the Womans Seed be fit Nutriment for the Mans, by reaſon of the moiſture and thinneſs of it, being more fit to frame and make up Conception thereby: for as of ſoft Wax and moiſt clay the Workman can frame what he intends, ſo the Mans Seed mixing with the Womans, as alſo with the menſtrual Blood, helps effectually to make the form and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect part of Man; or to give you a better compariſon, <hi>viz.</hi> as the Earth is to Plants, ſo is the Womb for Conception; for as the ſeed of every Plant requires the Earth to nouriſh and increaſe them, ſo the Seed of Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the Womb, which is affected with a deſire of off-ſpring, for by its moiſture and the help of the effluent Blood, it doth grow
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56968:19"/>and incoreaſe. Hence you may plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture what curious Art Nature uſeth in conceiving and framing a Child, which by an innate force grows up by degrees, and ſecretly inereaſing comes to maturity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> A ſerious diſcourſe of the Soul of Man: How it comes not from the Parents Seed, but is infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by God, and can neither dye nor corrupt: and what day of Child-bearing it is infuſed: of the Immortality thereof, and Certainty of the Reſurrection.</head>
               <p>THE Soul of Man is of ſo divine a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and excellency, that man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can in no wiſe comprehend it, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inſuſed breath of the Almighty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and incomprehenſible, but by him that gave it, it being, as it well may be termed, a part of himſelf; for <hi>Moſes,</hi> by Holy Inſpiration, relating the Original of Man, tells us, <hi>That God breathed into his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils the breath of Life, and he became a living Soul.</hi> Now as for all other Creatures, at his Word they were made, and had life,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56968:19"/>but the Creature that God hath appointed to let over his works, was favoured with the more immediate hand of the Almighty, forming him out of the duſt of the Earth, and ſecondly condeſcending to breath into his Noſtrils the breath of Life; which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies that there was more care, and (if we may ſo term it) labor uſed about man, than about all other Creatures or created things, he only partaking and participating with the divine Nature, being made in his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, bearing the Image of God, that is in innocence and purity, whilſt he ſtood firm; but in his Fall that lively Image was defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; yet ſuch was the inſinite love of God towards him, that alto' he rebelled againſt him, he would not altogether caſt him off, but found a way to reſtore him. Nay, ſo much in eſteem was he thought, not deſerving the leaſt favour, that the Son of God, the ſecond Perſon in the glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, when the fulneſs of Time was come, laying aſide his Crown of Stars, left the right-hand of Glory, Majeſty, &amp; the bright effulgence that adorned him, and deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, took upon him our nature. O infinite &amp; unſpeakable love. Nay more, indured ſhame reproach, ſcourging, buffetting, ſpitting on, and the death of the Croſs, that he might bruiſe the head of the Serpent, and deliver
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56968:20"/>beloved man from the jaws and brink of inter ruine; and the better to confirm his love towards us, is aſcended on high, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Captivity captive, where he is ſo far from forgetting us, that he is become our Mediator, and makes daily Interceſſion for us to the Father, whoſe offended Juſtice he has ſatisfied as to the Original Sin: but to come nearer to my purpoſe.</p>
               <p>If a man would underſtand the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Soul, as far as it is capable of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending it ſelf, let him after ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection deſcend into himſelf, and ſearch diligently his own mind, and there he ſhall find ſo many admirable Gifts and excellent Ornaments, that it muſt needs ſtrike him with Wonder and Amazement, as Reaſon, Underſtanding, true Choice, agility of Wit, Memory, and divers other Faculties, that abſolutely approve the Soul to be more admirable than that any ſhould imagine it to be finite or ſubject to Annihilation; yet by reaſon of its many Offices and Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whilſt in the Body it is ſpecified un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſundry denominations. For at <hi>St. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, when it enlivens the Body it is called the Soul; when it gives it knowledge the judgment, the mind, when it recalls things paſt, the memory, whilſt it diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erh &amp; diſcerneth, Reaſon, whiliſt it contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plates
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56968:20"/>she Spirit, whilſt it is in the ſenſitive parts of the ſenſes: and theſe are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Offices, whereby the Soul declares its. Power and performs its Actions; for pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the higheſt part of the Body, and neareſt Heaven, it diffuſeth or diſperſeth effectually its force into every Member, not proceeding from the Parents ſeed, nor mixed with groſs matter, but the infuſed breath of the Almighty immediately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from him, never paſſing from one to another, as fond and abſurdly the <hi>Pitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorians</hi> have inſinuated in their Opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Tranſmigration of the soul; and ſo vain were they, that they did not only ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the ſouls of deceaſed men paſſed into new born Infants, but into Beaſts alſo; and from thence it was they forbid the eating of Fleſh, and abſtained themſelves from ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, leſt, as they fondly fancied, they might as <hi>Tertullian</hi> records it, Eat their Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father in a Calf: but ſuch frivolous and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Notions are to be rejected by Chriſtians, and thoſe true ones obſerved which are both reaſonable and agreeable to humane Capacities; fot <hi>Orthodox Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> conclude in general, that the Soul is given to every Infant by Infant by Infuſion, when he or ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is perfected in the Womb, which happen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> about the 45 day after Conception; eſpecial
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56968:21"/>all for Males that in likelihood will be born at the end of nine Months, but that Females (who are of a weaker Conſtitution, and not ſo ſoon formed and perfected through the defect of heat) have not their Souls till the fiftieth day.</p>
               <p>And altho' this day in all caſes cannot be perfectly ſet down, yet <hi>Hypocrates</hi> has un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to give his abſolute opinion, when the Child has its perfect form, when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to move, and when born if in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for in his Book of the nature of Infants he affirmeth, That if it be a Male, and he be perfect on the thirtieth day, move at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tieth, he will come forth at the ſeventh Month: but if he be perfectly formed on he 35 day, he will move on the <hi>70th,</hi> and be born in the <hi>8th</hi> Month: again, if he be perfectly formed on the <hi>45th</hi> day, he will move on the <hi>90th</hi> day, and be born in the ninth Month. Now from theſe paſſings of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ays &amp; months, it plainly appears, that the day of Forming being doubled, makes up he day of moving; and that day 3 times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ckoned makes up the day of Birth.</p>
               <p>As for Example, where 35 perfect the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orm, if you double it, it makes 70; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay of motion and three times 70, amounts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 206 days or 7 months, allowing 30 days <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> one month, &amp; ſo you muſt conſider the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56968:21"/>reſt: But as for a Female, it is longer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting in the Womb, and the Mother ever goes longer with a Boy than a Girl, ſo that there is difference in the Accompt; for a Female formed in 30 days, moves not till the 70 day, and is born in the 7 Month; when ſhe is formed in the 40 days, ſhe moves on the 80 day, and is born in the 8 month: but if ſhe be perfectly formed on the 55 day, ſhe moves on the 90, and is born in the 9 month; but ſhe that is Formed on the 50 day moves on the 100 day, then will ſhe be born in the 10 month. And thus have I more largely demonſtrated it to the Reader, that he may know the reaſonable Soul is not in the Parents Seed, but is infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by God when the Child hath its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Form, and is exactly diſtinguiſhed in its Lineaments; for the Soul is not preent in the firſt month the Child begins to be formed, but the faculty of the Matrix, and force of the Seed perform the work by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, diſtinguiſhing the parts, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the form perfect.</p>
               <p>Now as the life of every other Creature, as it is teſtified in the 17 Chapter of <hi>Levitie is,</hi> is in the Blood, ſo the life of Man conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Soul; the which, although ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to paſſion, by reaſon of the groſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture of the Body, in which it has a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56968:22"/>confinement, yet it is immortal and cannot in it ſelf corrupt or ſuffer change, it being a ſpark of the divine mind, and a blaſt of Almighty Breath that diſtinguiſhes Man from other Creatures, and renders him immortal: and that every man has a peculiar Soul, it plainly appears by the vaſt difference between the Wit, Judgment, Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Manners, Affections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in men. And this <hi>David</hi> obſerves, when he ſays, <hi>God hath in particular faſhioned the Heart and Minds of all Men, and has given to every one its own Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a Soul of its own Nature.</hi> Hence <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> rejoyced, that God had given him a happy Soul, and a Body agreeable and ſuitable to it.</p>
               <p>It has cauſed many Diſputes amongſt the Learned, eſpecially <hi>Philoſopers,</hi> in what part of the Body the Soul chuſeth to reſide: and ſome have given their opinion, that its reſident is in the middle of the Heart, and from thence communicates it ſelf to every part; which <hi>Solomon,</hi> in the Fourth of his <hi>Proverbs,</hi> ſeems to aſſert, when he ſays, <hi>Keep thy Heart with all thy diligence, becauſe Life proceedeth therefrom:</hi> but many curious Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians ſcarching the Works of Nature in Man's Anatomy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do give it as their Opinion, that its chief Seat is in the Brain, from whence proceed the Senſes, Faculties,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56968:22"/>and Actions, diffuſing the operations of the Soul through all parts of the Body, whereby it is enlivened with heat and force; but it doth communicate particular force to be Heart by Arteries, Catotides, or ſleepy Arteries that part upon the Throat; the which if they happen to be broke, or cut, cauſe Barrenneſs, and if ſtopped they become Apoplectick; for there muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be ſome ways through which the Spirits animal and vital may have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and convey native heat from the Soul. For although the Soul is ſaid to reſide in one place, it operates in every part, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing every Member which are the Souls Inſtruments, by which ſhe manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her pow'r: but if it ſo happen that any of the Organical parts are out of Tune, the Work is confuied, as it may appear in the caſe of Idiots, Madmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though in ſome of them, the Soul by forcibly working recovers her ſupernatural vigor, &amp; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come right after a long diſpondency of mind and in ſome it is loſt in this life. For as fire under aſhes, nor the Sun obſcured from our ſight by thick Clouds, afford not their full luſtre, ſo the ſoul overwhelmed in moiſt or faulty matter, is darkned, and Reaſon thereby overclouded; and although reaſon ſhines leſs in Children than in thoſe that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56968:23"/>are arrived to maturity; yet no man muſt imagine that the Soul is an Infant, and grows up with the Child, for then would it again decay; but it ſuits it ſelf to the weakneſs of Nature, and the imbecility of Body wherein it is placed, that it may the better operate. And as the Body is more and more capable of receiving its influence, ſo it ſhews it ſelf in its prper luſtre, having its force and indowments at the time it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the formed Child in the Womb, for the Subſtance of it can receive nothing leſs: And thus much to prove that the Soul comes not from the Parents Seed, but is infuſed by God: and the next thing now to be handled is its Immortality; and thereby I ſhall demonſtrate the certainty of the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>That the Soul of Man is a divine Ray infuſed by God, I have already made appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and now come to ſhew you that whatever immediately proceeds from him muſt participate of his Nature, and from thence conſequently be as Immortal as it's Original; for although all other Creatures are indued with life and motion, yet wnat they a reaſonable Soul: and from thence 'tis concluded, their life is in their Blood, and that being corruptible, they periſh, and after their expiring are no more. But Man
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56968:23"/>being endued with a reaſonable Soul, and ſtamped with the divine Image, is of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent nature, and tho' his Body be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, yet his Soul cannot periſh, but muſt, when it is expunged its earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, return to God that gave it, either to receive reward or puniſhment: now that the body can ſin of it ſelf is impoſſible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wanting the Soul, it cannot act nor proceed to any thing either good or evil; for could it do ſo, additional ſins might be accumulated even in the Grave; but 'tis plain, that after death there is a ceſſation; for as Death leaves us, ſo judgment finds us. And St. <hi>John,</hi> in the fifth Chapter of his Goſpel, tells us, <hi>That the hour ſhall come, that all that are in their Graves ſhall hear his Voice, and they that have done well ſhall come forth to the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evil, to the Reſurrection of Condemnation.</hi> And Holy <hi>Job,</hi> in the fourteenth and nineteenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpeaking to the ſame purpoſes, ſays, <hi>For I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the Earth: And though after my Skin Worms deſtroy my body, yet in my Fleſh ſhall I ſee God: whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and mine Eyes ſhall behold, and not another, though my Reins be conſumed within me.</hi> By this 'tis plainly proved, that the Soul is made of immortal Eſſence, incapable
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56968:24"/>of death, having a place aſſigned it after its ſeparation from the Body, till the day of the general Reſurrection, not in the Grave, but in a Manſion prepared by the Almighty for its Reception; and that through the mighty working of him that is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf, it ſhall again enter the ſame Body that was laid down, tho' the duſt thereof be ſcattered to the four Winds of Heaven; nay, ſuch force and vigour ſhall it have, that it ſhall as it were take up the Body; for <hi>Job</hi> poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſays, <hi>I ſhall riſe out of the Earth at the laſt day,</hi> &amp;c. Which being applicable to the future <hi>Tenſe,</hi> may be meant two ways, I ſhall, or will riſe; for plainly foreſeeing the Reſurrection, he claimed it as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his Creator. Nay, ſo far were the Heathens, by the light of Nature, from doubting the immortality of the Soul, that <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Phaedro</hi> thus reaſons; <hi>viz. What conſiſts not of Elements</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is immortal and can neve dye. The Soul is not made of Elements nor of created matter, but came from God, and therefore it cannot dye,</hi> &amp;c. Then may it be without difficulty granted, that the body which has been a long Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Souls, will once again enjoy it never more to be ſeparated; for the Body at the Reſurrection ſhall be incorruptible,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56968:24"/>and ſo as far from a capacity of periſhing any more as the Soul; made ſo by him that at firſt created it. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Reſurrection, ſaith, <hi>He ſhall change our vile bodies, and make them like his glorious body.</hi> The conſideration of which, makes him in another place cry out, <hi>O the depth of the Riches, of the Wiſdom, and Knowledge of God! How unſcarchable are his Judgments, and his ways paſt finding out. For who hath known the mind of the Lord, or who hath been his Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor? For by him, and through him, and to him are all things.</hi> Nay, the Reſurrection of mans Body may be proved by the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many inconſiderable Creatures, and their returning to life after they ſeem dead, nay, ſome of them thereby alſo changed; as who hath not obſerved that when a Graſhopper is grown old, and hath caſt his skin, a lively new ſhrill inſect will come forth of it. From a dying &amp; ſluggiſh Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piller comes out a lively painted Butterfly. From Ants a winged Fly. The Silk-worm having ſpent her Bowels in weaving out her Web, after many days ſeeming dead and motionleſs, becomes a Butterfly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for increaſe by laying a number of Eggs, and then expires. But above all, the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> that the Learned <hi>Lactantius</hi> writes of, may put us in mind, if not confirmed to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56968:25"/>us the Reſurrection, for after ſhe has liv'd in the <hi>Arabian Fields</hi> (as ſome affirm) about 600 years, and finding her ſelf waſted with Age and infirmity, ſhe gathers the ſprigs of Caſſei, Myrrh, Frankincenſe and other Aromatick combuſtion, when labouring with her wings, ſhe firing them by the heat of the Sun, which in thoſe Countreys is exceſſive, ſhe expires upon the Funeral-Pile, when out of her Aſhes ſprings a Worm, and from that Worm another <hi>Phoenix,</hi> to ſupply her place, Nay, further doe we not behold Grain thrown into the ground, continue there for a ſeaſon as if loſt and dead, but when warmth and moiſture gives it force, it ſprings up, and bears a hundred fold: Yea, Herbs aud Plants whilſt Winter with his Icy Arms graſps the Earth, ſeem dead retiring as it were into the Grave, and wait the Reſurrection of the Spring. But to conclude as to this point the infinite love towards Man, may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him that he was not made to be anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilated, ſince the ſecond perſon of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity condeſcended to take his nature upon him. Even he who is the Wiſdom of the Father, and of whom the wiſe Man Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in the 3 of his <hi>Proverbs,</hi> viz. <hi>I was with God in the beginning before any thing was made: I was with him from Eternity, when he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56968:25"/>made the Heavens: I was there when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed in the depth by a Law: I was preent when he ſuſtained the Heavens above, and the Earth beneath: I was with him, ordering all things, and was continually delighting before him, recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating my ſelf in the Earth, and my delight was with the Sons of Men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Monſters and monſtrous Births, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof, according to the Opinions of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry learned Men, with ſerious conſiderations, whether Monſters are endued with reaſonable Souls.</head>
               <p>THat many monſtrous Births have happened contrary to the courſe of Nature, is evident, not only in this but in former Ages; wherefore I ſhall take ſome pains, for the ſatisfaction of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to inquire into the cauſe of ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous forms.</p>
               <p>Now a monſtrous habit or ſhape of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is contracted divers ways, as from Fear, ſudden Frights, extraordinary Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the influence of the Stars, too much or too little Seed, the Mothers ſtrange Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56968:26"/>and divers phantaſms which the mind conceive deform the body, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Children of an improper ſhape, and many times not perfect in either Sex: ſometimes the whole courſe of Nature is changed, either when the Seeds are vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or the Inſtruments of Generation unfit, ſot hat the natural Faculties, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate and form the Child, cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their Office exactly: for as the moſt ingenious Artiſt can bring nothing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection if his Materials be bad or out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſo Nature wanting the force of her Faculties, or not having fit matter, muſt of neceſſity proceed prepoſterouſly in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Child. As in the Art of melting of Mettals it may be obſerved, if the matter be impure and not well cleanſed, the Veſſels or Receiver <hi>Oblique,</hi> and full of windings, not well joynted, the Corners ſet awry, and full of Chinks or Plates; if looſed or holds ill together, it is apparent men caſt ill ſhaped Figures. So if the Womb or the Matter be unfit or ill tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, 'tis impoſſible, without an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary over-ruling Providence; but above all, unſeaſonable Copulation, or intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Venery, is the caue of ſo many mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous ſhapes.</p>
               <p>So the Low-Country Women, eſpecially
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56968:26"/>thoſe living near the Sea-ſide, being reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and troubled in Copulation, bring forth miſhapen <hi>Embrio's,</hi> or rude and deformed burthens, not only without motion, but ſome that pant and are alive, and theſe moſt commonly happen in caſe of Sailors or Mariners, who coming home raſhly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or run upon their Wives without any due regard to their menſtrual courſes, or the Wombs cleanſing it ſelf to the Seaſon of the year, or the Moon or Suns progreſs through the Celeſtial Signs, nor are the Women without regard to the health or ſhape of their poſterity, leſs deſirous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them after a long ſeparation, which is not only exceeding hurtful to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for thence proceed not monſterous or untimely Births only, but dangerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes often to thoſe who ſo raſhly proceed. The firſt is becauſe the Seed mixing with menſtrual Blood contracts an unnatural maſs of corrupt matter, which either turns to miſcarriage, abortion, or a Monſtrous and deformed Birth, for by that means the faculty of the Womb as I ſaid looſeth its force to Generation and Succeſs of breeding the Child, or if it try to come to any thing it is at moſt ſome monſterous Form, not ſhaped like a Man, unleſs in ſome parts, which after a long continuance in the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56968:27"/>Womb, will come forth with great pain and labour, not unlike to this, there is an Eflux that greatly troubles ſuch as by their inconſiderate raſhneſs are ſubject to it.</p>
               <p>Our Women, becauſe conception begins in the fourth Moon, when the terms flow down by force, &amp; that Planet in conjunction call it a Moon Birth, or many kinds. And ſome are of opinion that this conception may be made without the help of a Man, by force of Imagination, in thoſe that are extreamly Laſcivious; for that by often ſecing and touching their Husbands, at the ſame time ſtrongly fancying themſelves in the Act, their Seed flows to the Blood, and is by the heat of the Womb formed into a foul maſs, but arrives at no perfection. And to the ſame purpoſe it is when Men ſtrive againſt the Stream: entering into copulation in the fourth and ſilent Moon, and in the fourth day of its conjunction; for then not obſerving Natures Rules, he either loſes his Labour, or Generates a monſterous Birth, ot if it change, which is almoſt next to a miracle to be perfect, it is by the <hi>Latins</hi> called a Birth of the fourth Moon, becauſe the product is commonly unhappy in all the Series of its liſe, having had its enterance by Generation, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Natures order; which <hi>Moſes</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56968:27"/>or being ſo commanded by God, ſtrictly commanded the <hi>Hebrew</hi> men not to touch a Woman that was unclean of her Blood: and theſe that have been ſo raſhly profligate of either Sex, have many times by ſad experience found their wilful folly too late, but eſpecially the Female Sex; for by the violent concuſſion and motion uſed in copulation, and evil mixture, the contagion by degrees will ſeiſe upon the whole habit of the Body, cauſing the Pox and Leproſie: the like Effects it has upon Men, if the Woman be infected, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if he deal with Whores at ſuch times, who commonly are infected, and may be accounted ſo many walking Contagions, or Emiſſaries of the Prince of Darkneſs, for the deſtruction of Mankind, and at this day the greateſt peſt and grievance of the Nation.</p>
               <p>Theſe things rightly conſidered, no man need wonder at ſo many miſ-ſhapen Births and monſterous People with ſcald Heads, bowed and diſtorted Legs, Arms, and Backs, wry Necks, crumpled Feet, inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to ſwellings and inherent Diſeaſes, eſpecially ſwellings in the Groin, Buboes, and Emerods, as alſo that their minds are dull, ſtupid, forgetful, fooliſh, mad, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, which are indeed the effects of unſeaſonable and unreaſonable Venery,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56968:28"/>which every Creature but Man obſerves in the Seaſon Nature has allotted; and when their Females have conceived, they deſire no longer, but reſt ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>Therefore let Man, who is indued with a rational Soul, and ought above all other Creatures to have dominion over his appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite and affections, codſider how eruel he is to his poſterity that brings ſuch miſchiefs upon them, and chiefly they are here to be underſtood that are conceived in the fourth Moon, when the Womans Courſes are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, therefore all men ought to refrain, neither ſhould the Woman dare to copulate with Men, as better knowing the Seaſon of their Courſes than ſome raſh inconſiderate and unexperienced Novices of the Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Gender do; for the Children then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived want all or moſt of thoſe gifts and properties that Children begotten at ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able times are endowed withal, being capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of nothing that is good nor great; and if it ſo happen they do any thing well, they have ill Succeſs in their Undertakings, by reaſon their natural Faculties are ſhort, not by their own but their Parents fault, who undecently in Procreation violate Natures Law; whence it is that many things are wanting in them, or elſe given them ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, and with ſome ill qualities that <gap reason="missing" extent="16 pages">
                     <desc>〈16 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:56968:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Opinions of the Learned concerning Children conceived and born within the ſpace of ſeven Months, with lively Arguments upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, to prevent ſuſpicions of incontinency, and the bitter Conteſts that thereon too often ariſe between Man and Wife. To which is added, Rules for knowing the diſpoſition of Mans Body by the Genital parts.</head>
               <p>CErtain it is, that many bitter Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels have ariſen thro' miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, when ſolid reaſon would have rectified the Judgment, and have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the conception of such an evil; and from whence does this ariſe, but through Suſpicion and Jealouſie, when indeed it is many times founded upon a ſlender Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as the new married Womans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to Bed before the expiration of nine months, which is vulgarly taken from the time of Conception to the Birth: to remove which groundleſs Suſpicion, I ſhall endeavour, not that 'tis common dare I avouch, but that 'tis poſſible, and has been frequently known, that Children have been born at 7 months; but the matter being
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56968:29"/>wholly left by the Lawyers, who decide Controverſies to the Phyſicians to judge of, it is in their power to determine, by inſpecting the Child, whether it is a Child of 7, 8, 9, or 10 months. <hi>Paul</hi> the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor has this Paſſage in his nineteenth Book of Pleadings, <hi>viz.</hi> It is now a received truth, that a perfect Child may be born in the 7 month, by the Authority of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Hypocrates.</hi> And therefore we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that a Child born at the end of the 7th month, in lawful Matrimony, may be lawfully begotten. <hi>Gallen,</hi> in the 6th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his third Book, handleth this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but rather according to Mens Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons than according to the truth of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, or from natural Reaſons, who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth there is no certain time ſet for bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children. And from the Authority of <hi>Pliny,</hi> who makes mention of a Woman that went 13 months with Child: but as to what concerns the 7th month ſaith <hi>Lemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> I know many married People in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> that had Twins, who lived to extream Old Age, their Bodies luſty, and their Minds apt and lively; wherefore their Opinion is fooliſh, and or no moment, who aſſert that at 7 months a Child cannot be perfect and long lived, and that he cannot in all parts be perfect till
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56968:29"/>the 9th Month: and thereupon this Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author proceeds to tell a paſſage from his own knowlege, as follows: Of late <hi>ſaith he,</hi> there happened a great diſturbance amongſt us, which ended not without Blood ſhed; and was occaſioned by a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, whoſe Chaſtity had been violated, deſcending of a noble Family, and ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time held to be of unspotted fame. Now several there were who charged the Fact upon a Perſon of Note, <hi>viz.</hi> a Judge Preſident of a City in <hi>Flanders,</hi> who ſtrongly denyed the Fact, ſaying that he was ready to ſwear it upon the holy Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, that he never ſo much as penetrated her Body, or broke the Membrane of her Virginity, and that he would by no means therefore be taken for the Father of the Child that was not his: and further alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he verily believed that it was a Child born in ſeven Months, and that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was many miles diſtance from the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it when it was conceived, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Judges before whom the hearing was, decreed That the Child ſhould be viewed by Able Phyſicians, as alſo Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced Women, and that they ſhould make their report, who having made diligent inquiry, all of them with one accord, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the Child (without reſpecting
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56968:30"/>who was the Father) was a Child Born within the ſpace of Seven Months, that it was carryed in the Mothers Womb but 27 Weeks, and ſome odd Days, but if ſhe could have carried it to full 9 Months, the Childs Parts and Limbs would have been more firm and ſtrong, and the Sructure of the Body more compact and faſt, for the Skin was exceeding looſe, and the Breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone that defends the Heart, and the Sword-like Griſtie that lies over the Stomach were higher than naturally then ſhould be, not plain but crocked, and ſharp Ridged, or pointed like thoſe of young Chickens that are hatched at the beginning of the Spring. And being a Female Infant, it wanted its Nailes upon her Fingers, and the outmoſt Joynts of her Fingers upon which from the Muſculous or Cartilaginous matter of the Skin, Nails that are very ſmooth do come, and by degrees harden, ſhe had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Nails a thin Skin or Film: as for her Toes there was not the leaſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Nailes about them, by reaſon they wanted the heat that was communicated to the Fingers from the nearneſs of the Heart. Theſe and the like weighty matters being conſidered, and above all, one Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of quality that aſſiſted, affirming that ſhe had been the Mother of 19 Children,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56968:30"/>and that divers of them had been born, and lived a 7 Months, they without favour to any party made their report that the infant was a Child of 7 Months, and ſo muſt be accounted though it was born within the ſeventh Month, for that in ſuch caſes the revolution or circute of the Moon ought to be obſerved, which perfects it ſelf in 4 bare weeks or ſomewhat leſs then 28 days, in which ſpace of her revolution the Blood being agitated by the Moons force, the Courſes of the Woman flow from them, which being ſpent and the Matrix cleanſed from the Menſtrual Blood, which happens on the 5th day, then if on the 7th day a Man lye with his Wife, the copulation is moſt natural, and the conception beſt, and a Child then gotten may be born in the 7th Month, and prove very healthful, ſo that upon this report the ſuppoſed Father was pronounced innocent, upon proof that he was a hundred miles diſtance all that month in which the Child was begot: own as for the Mother ſhe ſtrongly denied that ſhe knew the Father, being forced in the dark and that through fear and ſurprize was left in ignorance: though <hi>Phyſitians</hi> are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that if a Woman prove with Child, it cannot be accounted a Rape, for unleſs ſhe caſt forth her Seed to commix with the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56968:31"/>Man (which imploys a willingneſs in her to be a Copartner in the Act,) the Child cannot be formed: but my opinion is, that poor ſilly Girls, ſtrugling to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in caſe of ſuch violence, and not in ſuch fear and perplexity regarding the ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cety of containing their Humour, the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Veſſels by an natural proneneſs will open, and the Seed in ſuch caſes, whether they deſire it or not, will flow, to commix with the Mans in the Matrix, and by coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating with the Blood that deſcends to nouriſh, it will form the Child: and thus much for theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>For for Copulation, it ought not to be had unleſs the Parties be in health, leſt it turn to the diſadvantage of the Childen ſo begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, creating in them, through the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ill humour, divers lingering and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Diſeaſes; wherefore Health is no where better to be diſcerned than by the Genitals of the Man, wherefore Midwives and other skilful Women, in former days were wont to ſee the Teſticles of Children, thereby to conjecture or gueſs at their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſtate of Body, and young men may know thereby the Signs or Symptoms of life and death, for if the caſes of the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles be looſe and feeble, and the Cods fall down, it denotes the natural faculties and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56968:31"/>vital Spirits, whichare the props of Life, are fallen: but if the Secret parts be wrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and raiſed up, the Yard, at any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo requiring, ſtanding ſtif, it is a Sign all will be well: but that the Event may exactly anſwer the Prediction, it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to conſider what part of the Body the diſeaſe poſſeſſeth: for if it chance to be the upper part that is afflicted, as he Head or Stomach, then will it not ſo well appear by the Members, which frequently are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned with ſuch grievances; but the lower part of the body exactly ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing with them, their livelineſs, on the contrary, makes it apparent; for Natures force and the Spirits that have their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, firſt manifeſt themſelves therein, which occaſions Midwives often to feel the Genitals of Children to know in what part the grief is reſident, and whether life or death be portended thereby, the Symptom being ſtrongly communicated by the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels that have their intercourſe with the principal Seats of Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:56968:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The cauſe of the Green ſickneſs in Virgins, with its Symptoms and Directions for its cure; To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the chiefeſt occaſion of Barrenneſs in Women, and by what means to remove the Cauſe, and render them fruitful.</head>
               <p>THE ſormer of theſe ill conveniencies is too apparent in Virgins, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as are of a Flegmatick Complexion, evidently ſhewing it ſelf by diſcolouring the Face, in making it look green, pale, or of a dusky yellow, which proceeds from raw undigeſted humours, nor only does it appear to the Eye, but ſenſibly afflicts ſuch as it poſſeſſes, with difficulty of breathing, pains in the Head, Palpitation of the Heart, unuſual beating and ſmall throbings of the Arteries in the Temples, Neck and Back, many times caſting them into Fevers, if the humour be very vicious, alſo loathing of meat, and diſtenſion of the Hypocondrick part, by reaſon of the inordinate reflux of menſtruous Blood to the greater Veſſels, and by reaſon of the abundance of humour, the whole body is often troubled with ſwelling, or if not at
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56968:32"/>leaſt the Thighs, Legs, and Ankles all above the Heels.</p>
               <p>Now this affliction proceeds from crude, raw, and undigeſted Humours ariſing from the ſuppreſſion of the monthly Courſes, by reaſon of the natural narrowneſs of the Veſſels, or their accidental Contraction by violent motion, but oftner through eating Chalk, Oat-meal, Tobacco-pipes, Loame, Starch, Nutmegs, and drinking of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, for thereby an ill Concoction in the Bowels is occaſioned, and the Humours moreover contracted into the habit of the body, become habitual, and concordant with it: many of theſe Afflictions happen through the long Retention of the Seed, when Virgins are ripe for the Act of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; which vitiating, the Veſſels ſpread it into evil Humours: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt thing neceſſary to eradicate the Cauſe, is matrimonial Conjunction, and ſuch Copulation as may prove to the ſatisfaction of her that is afflicted; for by that means the Humours being diffuſed and diſpreſſed, they will ſoon waſt themſelves, and then no more matter being admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to increaſe them, they will vaniſh, and a good temperament of Body will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn: but in caſe ſuch a Conjunction cannot be had ſo ſoon as neceſſity requires, then let
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56968:33"/>the Damſel blood in the Heel, and if ſhe be about 16, you may do it likewiſe in the Arm, though ſufer her not to bleed over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, eſpecially if any pure blood come forth, for then the vitiated Humour cling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Veins will ſtay behind, and that bloods loſs render her leſs capable to oppoſe them. If the diſeaſes be of any continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, then is itto be eradicated by purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, preparation of the Humour being firſt conſidered, which may be done by the Virgins drinking decoction of Guaicum, with Dittany of Creet: but the beſt Purge in this caſe ought to be made of Aloes, Agrick, Juice of Lavin, Succorrina; and for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſtructing of the Humour, take prepared Steel, Bazoar-ſtone, the Root of Scorzone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, and Oyl of Chriſtal in ſmall Wine, and let the Diet be moderate, but in no wiſe let Vinegar be uſed therewith, nor upon any other occaſion. And in ſo obſerving, the Humours will be dilated, diſſipated, and transfuſed, by which means the Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will return, and the Body be lively and full of vigour. And now ſince Barrenneſs daily occaſions diſcontent, and that diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent creates difference between Man and Wife, or by immoderate grief frequently eaſts the Woman into one or other violent Diſtemper; I ſhall ſomewhat largely treat thereof.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:56968:33"/>
               <p>This defect comes divers ways, but moſt commonly through the defect of the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, Veſſels, Blood or Menſtrum: and of theſe I ſhall diſcourſe in their order, and then proceed to mention other matters Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the ſame ſubject. The defect then in the Genitals frequently happens in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men through the ſtrict cloſure of the mouth of the Womb, which by that means denies the Seed entrance, or through the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſs of the parts or ſhare-bone, that will not admit the Yard entrance, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times by reaſon of ſome Ulcers of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies in the neck of the Womb, to which may be added the defect of the Seed, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome Diſtemper in the Generative Veſſels, which the Woman may perceive by the little, or no ſatisfaction ſhe receives in the act of copulation; ſometimes again Children are wanting, when the Woman being too young, her Courſes are not come down, or that ſhe is ſo old they ceaſe to flow: For tis the opinion of the Learned, that when the Courſes are wanting, the Man labours in vain, and further it may be attributed to the want of Seed, when there is not a due proportion of either Party, or when by reaſon of ſome cold moiſt Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours flowing into the Womb, it loſeth it's attractive force, and cannot draw the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:56968:34"/>Seed to its proper place or ſtation.</p>
               <p>Now if the Orifice of the Womb be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the Seed cannot enter, it muſt be opened by inciſion, or rather the two wings or Nymphae, which many times extend themſelves over the Clytoris, ſo far that the Yard cannot paſs the neck of the Womb: and ſubject to this defect in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are many Women, eſpecially in hot Countries, but moſt of all in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where the Chyrurgeons are forced with Silver In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, to make way for the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Generation, a thing not altogether unpracticable in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In caſe the neck of the Womb be ſo ſtrait that the Yard cannot enter, then is the caſe to be inquired into, whether it be natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, or proceed from ſome ſwelling, or Schirrhus either within or without, and if any ſuch thing appears, it is for the moſt part incureable, but if it be a natural ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then ſupple it with a Tent dipped in Oyl of Roses and the white of Eggs, and drink Chamomile Poſſer sweetned with Sugar-Candia, morning and evening: and by the operation thereof, the Womb which is of a reaching quality, will in all parts diſtend and give way to the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Generation, or if it so happen in a young Woman, Nature will increase the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56968:34"/>paſſage, and time produce things fitting to their mutual Satisfaction; but let no man by violence endeavour in attempting Copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to force the Paſſage, leſt he break the Veſſels, nay indanger the Bladder it ſelf, which has been broke with ſuch violent Intruſion, and ſo coſt the Woman her life.</p>
               <p>If the neck of the Womb be ulcerated, or any Excreſenſes happen there, which equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder Copulation, then may they be known by the pain and ſhooting upon the leaſt compreſſure, and the iſſuing forth of putrid Humours, and ſometimes Blood if the Ulcers be great, and the Terms flow, the Water hot, pains ariſing in the fore part of the Head, and oftentimes they oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion gentle Fevers.</p>
               <p>And theſe Obſtructions of Generation happen divers ways, as from external cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>viz.</hi> Raſh Phyſick, hard Labour, or exceſſive Copulation; from internal cauſes, as the Corruption of the Secundine, the Courſes too long retained, or obſtructed heat, and overflowing of the Urinal Veſſels, Virulent Gonorrhaeas, Pox, Inflammation turned into Apoſtume, Humours flowing from divers parts of the Body, and ſetling there; all which muſt be duely conſidered.</p>
               <p>Now ſome are in the outward part, and may be the eaſier come at, and external
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56968:35"/>plications as are moſt convenient applied thereto; but thoſe that cannot be come at, muſt be cured if poſſible by injection: the beſt injection in this caſe is as follows; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Break four Eggs, and take the Whites only, the which beat with an equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Roſe-water, mingled with Plantain-water, Litherage of Gold, Camphire, Bole-Armonick, Ceruſe, of each a dram, half a dram of Green Copperas, all which well beaten, diſſolved, and mixed together, ſtrained through a fine Cloath, and with a Syrringe inject it Morning and Evening till the grief ceaſe; and if it ſmart that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well endured, you may ſometimes inject warm Milk to cleanſe the puttified matter.</p>
               <p>Others there are that are not ſo violent, and therefore admit of any eaſie Cure, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t being ſo deep, known by a putrid Greeniſh matter that flows from them. To cure this, take Water wherein Barley has been boiled, Honey of Roſes, new Milk and Sugar, with the decoction of Lentils, and after them gentle Aſtringents muſt be applied. Some again are ſordid, having much contagious Humour flowing from them; to cure which, ſtronger Medicaments muſt be applied: others there are that eat into the Fleſh, having a green Contagion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56968:35"/>flowing from them, to cleanſe which Aloes and Wormwood concocted in white Wine are moſt requiſite.</p>
               <p>Another ſort of Ulcers there are which appear long cating away the skin from off the Neck of the Wood, and are diſcerned by the Blood and pain the occaſion, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly upon the concreſſion appearing in the Neck of the Womb, much like Chilblains, occaſioned by ill lying, extraordinary Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by violent inflammation or flux of ſharp humours: The beſt cureafter a gentle purge, is an aſtringent Glyſter, and after that to anoint them with the Greaſe that fryes out of a Ladle often uſed in a Kitchen, when it is held to the fire, mixed with an oyntment called Pomarum, if the defect be in the Seed through tenderneſs of age in the Woman, ſo that her menſtrual Blood not coming down, flow not to it, then the beſt remedy is, convenient diet, moderate exerciſe and temperate Air, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with patience in the main, till nature in proceſs of time operates ſo effectually that all things appear and conſpire to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>If the Woman be ſtricten in years, and it ceaſe to be with her after the Cuſtom of Women, that is her Courſes are ſtayed, which in ſome happens ſooner, and in ſome
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56968:36"/>later, and between 44 and 55 with all them unleſs ſtrong preparatives, <hi>viz.</hi> an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary diet, eaſie longing, and moderate exerciſe reſtore them, thoſe Woman muſt deſpair of further Generation: for as the learned in this Art frequently obſerve, where there is neither Buds nor Bloſſoms there can to no Fruit.</p>
               <p>If any obſtruction happen in the Veſſels of Generation, that the Seed has no free paſſage, then the cauſe muſt be enquired into, and this often happens, the which is known by the ſmall deſire to Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery, and the little or no pleaſure or ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction received thereby, a ſettling in the Courſes, and a ſlimy F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gmatick matter mixed therewith, as alſo by their inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate flowing occaſioned by the plenty of humours collected in the Womb, which by reaſon of the abundant of windy Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours contracted therein cauſes obſtruction, to which may be added the cruditie and wateryneſs of the Seed, which debars the pleaſure in ejection, and from hence it is that ſudden paleneſs ariſes in the face, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To remedy this, the party muſt alter her Diet, not eating any cold, raw, Flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſubſtance, but rather ſuch things as are apt to ſtir up Cholerick, hot humours in the Body, as Anniſeeds, or Carraway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:56968:36"/>in her Bread, Store of Peniroyal in her Broth, let her likewiſe each morning for a week together make a Poſſet, in which ſhe muſt boil the Roots of Birthwort, Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, Sage, Roſemary, Cinamon and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: The takeing the Male Herb <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Dittany, Centaury, Marygolds, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds, Safron, Mugwort and Clovegilly-flowers, of each a handful, boil them in white Wine, and eject the Concoction by little and little at ſundry times, as the cold or obſtruction can be perceived, Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Belly and Reins of the back, one day with Oyl of Cinamon, the next with Oyl of Nutmeg or Mace, and the 3d. with Oyl of Myrrh, and ſo continuing to do for a month together. When the Woman lies down, Nature will be wonderfully reſtored and recover ſuch force as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to Obſtructions.</p>
               <p>Barrenneſs is likewiſe cauſed through want of due proportion of Seed in either party, to remedy which, let their Diet be ſuch as I have preſcribed in the former part of this Book, <hi>Chap.</hi> II. Many there are that conceive Barrenneſs is frequently cauſed by inchantation, but thoſe opinion s are altogether frivolous and vain.</p>
               <p>If the Womb be defective in attracting the Seed ejected, Men frequently labour in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:56968:37"/>vain: in ſuch a caſe the Woman muſt avoid Sorrow, Anger, or much Sleep, Eating new Cheeſe, Milk, and raw food, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Lettis, Endive, Spinage, Beets, Nuts, Cherries, Purſtain, Oynions Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and the like, They all being hurtful to Generation: nor muſt ſhe drink nor uſe Vinegar, nor eat the Fat of Meat too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, but the Womb muſt be cleanſed from the over abundant moiſture, with the decoction of Hearts Tongue (a Herb ſo called) Cummin, Fenel, and Anniſeed, and ſtrengthned with the Sirup of Wormwood, and for a gentle opperative Purge in this caſe, take half an ounce of Laudanun, Beeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wax, Sheeps Suet, and Agarick, of each a like quantity, melt and bruiſe them, after which make them up into little Pills and take 3 in a morning, and next to them take of this conception to the bigneſs of an Nutmeg, <hi>viz.</hi> The ſhavings of Ivory, Aſh Keys, Yellow and wild Rape-ſeed, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Montanus, with red and white Behen, of each one Dram, Cinaman, Galinga, Long-pepper, Cloves and Mace Balſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Roſemary Flowers, <hi>Blatiae, Beza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> Gentle Marjorum and Pennyroyal, of each 4 Scruples, Balm, Bogluſs, Cittern, Reils, of each two Scruples, Pearl diſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or beaten to power one Scruple, Musk
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:56968:37"/>two Grains, White-Sugar one pound and a half, bruiſe them and ſeeth them over a gentle fise, in as much Malmſey as will make them into a Confection. This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is indeed a moſt ſingular and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved one in all caſes of Barrenneſs, where cold or obſtructions of the Veſſels do occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion weakneſs in the Womb.</p>
               <p>Other cauſes of Barrenneſs there are when the Woman grows far, ſo that the Caul ſwelling and bearing beyond its Bounds with its fatneſs, obſtructs the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage into the Womb; to prevent which, the Woman muſt not ſleep over much, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the day time, nor feed riotouſly, but exerciſe her ſelf in walking, or mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Exerciſes, and often uſe Purgation and ſtrong Glyſters made of ſuch Herbs and Drugs that are hot and dry, which will in a ſhort time remove ſuch Obſtructions.</p>
               <p>But a more dangerous cauſe of Barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than yet I have named, are the Whites which are contracted by an inordinate Eurudition of an excrementitious Humour, collected through the Vitiouſneſs of the Blood, incident to Yonng and Old, at ſuch times as they are capable of Generation; and therefore the Cure muſt be haſtned by reaſon that in ſhort time it derides Art, and renders Women inevitably barren, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:56968:38"/>Leanneſs, Conſumption, Melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Dropſie, falling of the Womb, ſwoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Convulſions, which renders it diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and dangerous in long continuance, though in the beginning it may be eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. In the Cure of this, let <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> or Blood letting, be avoided, for as much as the bad Humour muſt be by no means recalled to defile the Blood, the Diſeaſe it ſelf being a ſufficient weakning of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and vital Spirits. Firſt, then to diſcuſs the Humour, in order to its Expurgation, take two ounces of Guaicum, the like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of China, and Lentick-wood, decoct them in Water and Honey, drinking a pint freſh made each morning: then to dry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p the Contraction of the Veſſels, or Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour that lodged there, take the Root of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilipendula, beat it to powder, and drink it in White-wine Morning and Evening: as alſo for Aſtringents, uſe Bones burnt and beat to powder, likewiſe the aſhes of Capons Dung ejected after a long time ſteeping in fair water: the Patient muſt likewiſe avoid ſleeping upon her Back, leſt the Humour deſcend and contract in the Veſſels of the Womb, but let her be rubbed often to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe them, that they ſettle not in any one place.</p>
               <p>Sometimes this occaſion of Barrenneſs
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:56968:38"/>happens through the violent attraction of the VVomb, and then appears ſigns of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of the Womb, the Fiux not being ſo great, to cure which Suffumarions are the moſt proper, and thoſe may be made of Frankinſence, Laudanum, Santa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, or Maſtick: the Woman upon ſuch occaſion, having great regard to her ſelf that ſhe take not cold, or proceed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate Diet.</p>
               <p>Many women there are whoſe violent luſt contracts a heat that deſtroys the Seed, and renders it incapable of coagulating, and mixing with the Blood, which very ſparingly on such occaſions flow from the several parts to the womb: In this case 'tis requiſite to avoid hot Air, soft lying, hot Meats and Spices, and requiſite to bleed in the Baſilick Vein, and Purge moderately with Electuary <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m de Epithijmo,</hi> and juice of Roſes, each two drams and a half, Whey half a pint, mix them together and drink them faſting in the morning, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue 4 hours after, or for want of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, you may take <hi>Triphera Saraſenicia</hi> and Rhuberb, of each half a dram, pulverized and mixed with 2 ounces of Syrup of Roſes, Violets, or Endive; but the moſt excellent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorative to cool and moderate the Temper in this caſe, is a Diet drink made as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:56968:39"/>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> Take Piſtacho, Pingles, and Eringoes, of each half an ounce, of Saffron a Dram, Lignum, Alloes, Gallinga, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryophillata, Mace, red and white Behen, and Baulm flowers, of each 4 Scruples, ſhavings of Ivory, Rind of Caſſia, each two Scruples, Syrup of Confected Giner twelve ounces. White Sugar ſix ounces, add to theſe 12 ounces of Baulem water, and ſet them over a gentle Fire, permitting them to ſeeth, then take it off, ſuffer it to cool, and put more water to it, ſtiring the ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, laſtly increaſing them with a Scruple and a half of Musk and Amber, then ſtrain out the Liquid prt and boil it up again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Conſerve, of which let the Woman eat 3 times a day, but not exceeding the bigneſs of a Walnut at a time. The times moſt convenient are Mornings, Noons, nad Nights, and this let her continue till ſhe finds her body in good temper.</p>
               <p>Another occaſion of Barrenneſs proceeds from the obſtruction of the Courſes, in which caſe open the Baſilick Vein, and take from thence a moderate quantity of Blood, after which take <hi>Hiera compoſita,</hi> and <hi>Oppopanax,</hi> of each half a dram, and a dram of Syrup of Gilliflowers, make them into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pills, take them in the Morning and ſleep upon them a conſiderable time, then
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:56968:39"/>drink off half a pint of Sugered water, and 3 hours after, a portion of Syrup of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat compounded: for want of this take Syrup of Eupatory 3 quarters of an ounce, Female-Mugwort, and Elecampaine Root, of each an ounce, with Syrup of Vinegar a proportionable quantity, mix them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and take them, when made into an Electuary, Morning and Evening, to the quantity of an Hazel Nut at a time; and if the Courſes flow not within a ſhort time after, let a peſſary of Musk, Amber, Wood of Aloes, and Aſh-Keys, of each 2 Grains, Saffron half a Scruple, Hares Renet an ounce, be put into the Womb Tent-wiſe, and continue there for the ſpace of a day, and it will remove the Obſtruction, cauſe the Courſes to flow, and in ſhort time ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Woman capable of Generation. And thus, Reader, have I, with much cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, performed my promiſe in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; and the next thing I ſhall proceed to, amongſt other matters relating to the Myſtery of Generation, are the ſigns of Virginity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:56968:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Virginity what it is, in what it conſiſts, and how violated; together with the Opinions of the Learned in the point of mutation of Sexes in the Womb, during the Operation of Nature in framing the Body.</head>
               <p>SEeing many ignorant people have boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted their Knowledge as to the firſt Particular, and ſome Virgins have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone hard Cenſures through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Determinations of ſuch as have taken upon them to diſcuſs the matter; I thought it altogether neceſſary to clear the Point, that ſo for the future the Conceited might not be indulged in their vain opinion, nor by traducing others prejudice the Female Sex, whoſe vertues are frequently ſuch as do not only require our admiration, but imitation. Then ſince the myſterious word Virginity has puzled many to define it, I mean the cauſe from whence it ariſes, for the Word barely in it ſelf ſignifies the prime chief, or beſt of any thing: but as to the point in hand, the main matter bears the following Conſtruction. It is obſerved by the curious Searchers into Natures Secrets,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:56968:40"/>that in young Maids or Females, that in the Secret place about the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus Pudoris,</hi> or rather by ſome vulgarly called the Neck of the Womb, is that pendulous production by ſome called the Hymen, but more right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Clauſtrum Virginale,</hi> and in <hi>French</hi> it is termed the <hi>Button de Roſe,</hi> or Roſes Bud, for that it much reſembles the Bud of a Roſe, expended, or a Clove Gilliflower, from whence it derived the Word <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>floro,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flower, or the deflowring of Virgins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe moſt are of opinion that the Virginity is altogether annihilated when this Dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is fractured and diſſipated by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and that when it is found perfect and intire no penetratio has been made. Alſo ſome learned <hi>Phyſicians</hi> are of opinion, that there is no other Hymen or Skin expand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed containing Blood in it, which divers imagine, in the firſt Copulation, flows from the fractured expanſe.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Clauſtrum Virginale,</hi> or Flower, is as it were compoſed or conſiſting of 4 Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runcles, or little Buds like Mirtle-berries, which in Virgins are full and plump, but in Women flag and hang looſe; and theſe are placed in the four Angles of the <hi>Sinus Pudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> joyned or held together by little Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes and Ligatures like Fibres, each of them ſituate in the Intreſticles or Spaces
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:56968:41"/>between each Caruncle, with which in a manner they are proportionably diſtended, which Membranes being once delacerated, denote devirgination, and many curious Coxcombs prying into this Secret the firſt night of their Marriage, and finding their Wives defective in this point, have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver after held them in evil eſteem, concluding it happened thro' the effect of Copulation with ſome other, who had been enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Chambers of <hi>Venus.</hi> Nay, one I knew that upon this vain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ancy took ſuch conceit, that he would never copulate with his Wife: when to undeceive ſuch Idiots, it is affirmed by the Learned, that ſuch fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture may happen divers ways by accident as well as Copulation with man, <hi>viz.</hi> by extraordinary ſtraining, violent coughing, immoderate ſneezing, ſtopping of Urine, and violent motion of the Veſſels, inforcibly ſending down the humours, which preſſing for paſſage, break the Ligatures or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane, ſo that the intireneſs or fracture of this thing, commonly taken for the Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Maiden-head, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o abſolute Sign of diſhoneſty: tho' certain it is, that in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation 'tis more frequently broke than otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Once at an Aſſize held for the County of <hi>Rutland,</hi> a young Man was put upon Tryal
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:56968:41"/>of life and death, which Tryal was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon an indictment, for forcing a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, when after divers queſtions asked, and the Maid ſwearing poſitively to the matter, naming the time, place, and manner of the Action, it was upon mature Deliberation reſolved, that ſhe ſhould be ſearched by a skilful Chirurgeon and two Midwives, who were to make their report upon their Oaths, which after due Examination they accordingly did affirm, that the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes were intire and unfractured, and that it was their Opinion, for that reaſon, that her Body had not been penetrated, which ſo far wrought with the Jury, that the Priſoner was acquitted, and the Maid afterward confeſſed ſhe ſwore againſt him out of revenge, becauſe he had promiſed to marly her, and then declined it. And thus much concerning Virginity: and now I ſhall proceed to the ſecond particular, which is, <hi>Reader,</hi> to ſhew you the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of divers learned men to relation to Natures operation in changing Sexes in the Womb.</p>
               <p>This Point is of much neceſſity, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the different Opinions of Men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to it. Therefore before any thing poſitive can be aſſerted, it will be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther convenient to recite what has been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:56968:42"/>as well in the negative as the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative. And firſt of the firſt <hi>Severius Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> who argues for the negatives writes thus. The Genital parts (ſaith he) of both Sex, are ſo unlike each other, in Subſtance, Compoſition, Scituation, Figure, Action and Uſe, that nothing is more unequal, and by how much more all other parts of the body, (the Breſts excepted, which in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſwell more, becauſe of their ſecondary uſe) have an exact reſemblance ſo much the more, in reſemblance are the Genital parts of one Sex, compared with the other una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and if their Figure he thus different, much more is their uſe, for Women contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the matter, but Men the form in caſe of Generation. The Venerial Appetite alſo proceeds from different cauſes, for in Men it proceeds from a deſire of Emiſſion, and in Women from a deſire of Completion, in Women alſo the chiefeſt of thoſe parts are concave and apt to receive, but in Men they are only porous, and in a Woman Solid.</p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered, I cannot but wonder (added he how any one can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the Genital Member of Female Births ſhould be changed into thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Males) ſince by thoſe parts only the difference and diſtinction of Sexes is made,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:56968:42"/>nor can I well impute the reaſon of this vulgar Error to any thing but the miſtake of unexpert Midwives, who have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the evil conformation of the parts which in ſome Male Births may have happened to have had ſome ſmall protru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, not to have been diſcerned as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the example of a Child Chriſtned at <hi>Paris,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Joan,</hi> as if it had been a Girl, when as afterwards it proved a Boy, and on the contrary the over-far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of the <hi>Clytoris</hi> in Female Births, may have occaſioned the like miſtakes. Thus far <hi>Plinaeus</hi> proceeds in the negative, yet notwithſtanding his negation there are not wanting divers learned Phyſicians that have aſſerted the affirmative, of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Galen</hi> is one, a Man (ſaith he) is differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent from a Woman in nothing elſe but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Genital members without his body: and this is certain, that if Nature having formed a Man, would convert him into a Woman; ſhe hath no other task to perform, but to turn his Genital member inward, &amp; a Woman into a Man by doing the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But this is to be underſtood of the Child when it is in the Womb, and not perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly formed, for divers times Nature hath made a Female Child, and it has ſo remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Belly of the Mother for a month
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:56968:43"/>or two, and afterward plenty of heat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in the Genital Members, upon ſome occaſion they have iſſued forth, and the Child has become a Male, yet retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome certain Geſtures, unbefitting the Maſculine Sex, as Female Actions, a ſhrill Voice, and more feeble than ordinary, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, Nature often having made a Male, and cold Humours flowing to it, the Genitals have been inverted, yet ſtill retaining a Man like faſhion, both in Voice and Geſture.</p>
               <p>Now theſe opinions conſidered, I am rather inclinable to believe the latter as a thing altogether probable, for there is not that vaſt difference between the Members of the two Sexes, as <hi>Plinaeus</hi> would have us believe there is, for the Woman has in a manner the ſame Members with the Man, though they appear not outwardly, but are inverted for the conveniency of Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the main difference being that one is more ſolid than the other, and that the chief reaſon of changing Sexes is, and muſt be attributed to heat or cold ſuddainly or ſtowly contracted, which operates accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to its greater or leſſer force. And thus much for theſe two particulars, leaving which I ſhall proceed to lay down ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and neceſſary inſtructions or directions
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:56968:43"/>for Midwives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> opening in that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe a Cabinet of many rare Secrets not vulgarly known, and indeed only fiting to be known to ſuch as may obſerve and put them in practice for the publick good, and in no wiſe convert them to obſcenity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> A Midwife, how ſhe ought to be qualified.</head>
               <p>THoſe that undertake this great task, ought by no means to enter upon it raſhly or unadviſedly, but with all imaginable caution, well eighing and preconſidering that ſhe is accountable for all the miſchief that befalls thro' her wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ignorance or neglect; therefore let not unskilful Women take upon them this Office, barely upon pretence of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity of Years and Child-bearing, for in ſuch for the moſt part there are divers things wanting that ought to be obſerved, which is the occaſion ſo many Women and Children are loſt: now as for a Midwife, in relation to her Perſon theſe things ought to be obſerved, <hi>viz.</hi> She muſt not be too
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:56968:44"/>old nor too young; neither extraordinary fat, nor weakned by leanneſs, but in a good habit of Body, not ſubject to Diſeaſes, Fear, nor ſudden Frights; her Body well ſhaped, and neat in her attire, her Hand ſmooth and ſmall, her Nails ever paired ſhort, not ſuffering any Rings to be upon her Fingers during the time ſhe is doing her Office, nor any thing upon her Wriſts that may obſtruct: and to theſe ought to be added Activity &amp; a convenient Strength, with much cution and diligence: not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Drowzineſs nor Impatience.</p>
               <p>As for her Manners, ſhe ought to be courteous, affable, ſober, chaſt, and not ſubject to Paſſion; bountiful and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate to the Poor, and not covetous when ſhe attends upon the Rich.</p>
               <p>Her Temper chearful and pleaſant, that ſhe may the better comfort her Patients in their Afflictions: nor muſt ſhe at any time make over-much haſt, tho' her buſineſs be urgeht in another place, leſt by indanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mother or the Child ſhe diſgrace her Self, and forfeit Heavens Bleſſing upon her Endeavours for the future.</p>
               <p>Of Spirit ſhe ought to be prudent, wary and cunning, but above all, to have the fear of God before her Eyes, and to imploy the Talent he has lent her to his Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:56968:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Things worthy to be obſerved by Midwives, tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Advancement, and what they ought to avoid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LET her that undertakes this Office, attended with many circumſtances of danger and diſgrace, take good heed to what I ſhall relate. In the firſt place, let her be diligent to leave nothing unſearched which may be advantagious to her practice, never imagining her ſelf ſo perfect but ſhe may add to her Knowledge by ſtudy and experience; yet never let her apply any remedies in that caſe, unleſs ſhe has tryed them, or known them tryed with Succeſs, or at leaſt is conſcious of their force, that they will do no harm, doing nothing in that nature, to practice upon poor or rich, but ſpeaking freely of what ſhe knows, and giving reaſon for the farther Confirmation thereof, by no means daring to give directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for ſuch Medicines as will cauſe Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to pleaſure thoſe that have unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceived, which to do, is a high degree of Wickedneſs, and may be ranked with Murther: but if any come to her with ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:56968:45"/>pretences, let her ſend them to able <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and neither for fair words nor lucre be won to hearken to them. If ſhe be ſent for, let her know to whom ſhe goes, and be careful therein, leſt by laying any one that has an infectious Diſeaſe, as the Pox, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhe get it, and ſo ſpoil other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as a Midwife once did, who laying a Strumpet, that had an inveterate Pox, which occaſioning a Bubo upon her right hand, and ſhe not leaving off her Calling, ſpoiled divers Women, nor the Women only, but the Men alſo, to whom it was communicated by their Wives, which made them think hard of each other, and for a long time could not imagine how it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; but at laſt it was diſcovered by an able <hi>Phyſician,</hi> and the Midwife for ever after barr'd her Practice, and not ſo only, but followed with Curſes even to her Grave. She muſt likewiſe obſerve, that ſhe enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains no great belly'd Women at Bed and Board in her Houſe, leſt thereby ſhe bring a Scandal upon her Self, and ſo loſe her Practice. If the Birth at any time be hard and difficult, ſhe muſt not be diſmayed, but chear up the Woman, and try her utmoſt Skill to make the Labour eaſie, Directions for which ſhall hereafter be incerted; nor muſt ſhe ever think of any thing but doing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:56968:45"/>well, and uſing her utmoſt skill, cauſing all neceſſary things that are proper for the work, conſolation of the Woman, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Child to be in a readyneſs; and above all let her uſe her diligence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by perſwaſion or otherwiſe, to keep the Woman from being unruly in her pangs, leaſt thereby ſhe deſtroy both her ſelf and her Child, and not in any wiſe to proceed too haſty in her buſineſs, but wait Gods leaſure in all things, and by no means let her ſuffer her wits to ſcatter, by diſmay or doubt, if things go not well, for fear it diſorders the ſenſes, and a Perſon that keeps her wits together, is capable of give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſiſtance in weighty affairs, for when we are moſt at a plunge, then there is moſt need of prudence to ſet things right. And ſeeing ſhe can never be an expert Midwife that has no further knowledge than of the external parts, I ſhall not think it amiſs briefly with modeſty, to proceed in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing the generative part of Woman; as they have been Anatomized, by the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the preſent and paſt ages, and ſhew the uſe of ſuch Veſſels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as are contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to Generation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:56968:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of the Genitals of Women, External and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to the Veſſels of the Womb.</head>
               <p>WAs it not for the benefit of Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners and Profeſſors of the Art of Midwifry, I ſhould above all things ſpare to Treat of theſe particulars becauſe they may be turned by ſome Laſcivious and lude Perſon into ridicule, but they being abſolutely neceſſary to be known. I will hope the beſt, and proceed in order.</p>
               <p>At the Bellies Inferior parts is the <hi>Pubis</hi> where when Virgins come to maturitie; Nature has ordained a covering of Hair to hide as it were the Secret parts, and ſhroud 'em from any ill conveniency, when deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending downward there appears two clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Fleſh as it were Lips, which are the Portals of the Pallace of Generation, giving enterance into the more Secret and Abſtruſe parts, and between theſe being the Exterior Orifice, it is properly called the privy Member compoſed of protuber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and are accounted two ſoft oblong bodies, compoſed of Skin and a ſpongy kind of Fleſh.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:56968:46"/>
               <p>The next things that offer are the <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phae</hi> and Clytoris; the former of which are of a Membrany and flimy Subſtance, ſpongy, ſoft, and partly Fleſhy, being of a bloody colour, in the ſhape of Wings, two in number, though from their riſe they are joyned in an acute Angle, producing there a fleſhly Subſtance which cloaths the Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris, and many times they ſpread ſo far, that inciſion is required to make way for the Mans Inſtrument of Generation.</p>
               <p>The Clytoris is a ſubſtance in the upper part of the Diviſion, where the two Wings concur and is the Seat of venerial Pleaſure, being like a Yard in Situation, Subſtance, Compoſition and Erection, growing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of the Body two Inches, but that rarely happens, unleſs thro' extream luſt or extraordinary accident. But to proceed, this Clytoris conſiſts of two ſpongy and skinny Bodies, containing a diſtinct Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal from the <hi>Pubis</hi> Bone, the Head of it being covered with a tender skin, having a hole or paſſage like the Yard of a Man tho' not quite through, in which, and the bigneſs, it only differs from it.</p>
               <p>The next things in courſe are the Fleſhy Knobs, and the great Neck of the Womb. And theſe Knobs are behind the Wings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing four in number, much reſembling Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:56968:47"/>berries, being placed in quadrangle one againſt the other, and in this place is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed the Orifice of the Bladder, which opens it ſelf into the Siſſure to evacuate the Urin, for ſecuring of which from Cold, or the like inconveniency, one of theſe Knobs are placed before it, and ſhuts up the Paſſage.</p>
               <p>The Lips of the Womb that next ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, being ſeparated, diſcloſe the Neck thereof, in which two things are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>viz.</hi> The Neck it ſelf, and the <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> but more properly the <hi>Clauſtrum Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginule,</hi> of which I have before diſcourſed. By the Neck of the Womb is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, the Channel that is between the aforeſaid Knobs, and the inner Bone of the Womb which receives the Yard like a Sheath; and that it may the better be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated for the pleaſure of Procreation, the Subſtance of it is ſmewy and a little ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and in this Concavity are divers folds or Orbicular Plights made by Tunicles, wrinkled like an expanded Roſe; in Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins they plainly appear, but Women that have been uſed often in Copulation they are extinguiſhed; ſo that the inner ſide of the Wombs Neck appears ſmooth, and in old Women it becomes more hard and grifley: And now note, that although this
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:56968:47"/>channel be ſometimes writhed and crooked ſinking down, yet in the time of copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, labour, or the monthly Courſes, it is erected and extended, which over Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion occaſioned the great pain in Child-Birth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hymen</hi> or <hi>Clauſtrum Virginale,</hi> is that which cloſes the Neck of the Womb, being as I have before cited in the Chapter relating to Virginity, broken in the firſt copulation, its uſe being rather to ſtay the untimely Courſes in Virgins than to any other end, and commonly when it is broke in copulation or by any other accident, a ſmall quantity of Blood flows, with ſome ſmall pain paſſing. Hence it is obſerved that between the duplicitiy of the two Tunicles which conſtitute the Neck of the Womb, there are many veins and arteries running along, and ariſing from the Veſſels, deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on both ſides the Thighs, and paſſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Neck of the Womb, being extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly large, and the reaſon of their largements is for that the Neck of the Bladder requires to be filled with abundance of Spirit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be extended and dilated for its bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taking hold of the Yard, great heat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing requied in ſuch motions, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming more intenſe by the act of fricati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, does comſume a conſiderable quantity
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:56968:48"/>of moiſture in ſupplying, which large Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are altogether neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Another cause of the longneſs of theſe Veſſels there is, <hi>viz.</hi> By reaſon the month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Courses have their way through them which often occaſions Women with Child to continue their purgations, for although the Womb is ſhut up, yet the paſſage in the Neck of the womb through which theſe Veſſels paſs, are open: In this cauſe there is further to be obſerved, that as ſoon as you penetrate the Female Siffure or <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum,</hi> there appear two little pits or holes, wherein is contained a contract hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, which by being expugned in time of Copulation, greatly delights the Woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> A deſcription of the Wombs Fabrick, the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Veſſels, and Tiſticles in Women, as alſo of the different, or Ejaculatory Veſſels.</head>
               <p>IN the lower part of the Hypogaſtrion, where the Lips are wideſt and broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt (they being greater and broader thereabouts, then thoſe of Men, which is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:56968:48"/>the reaſon they have likewiſe broader But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks then men,) is the womb joyned to its Neck, and is placed between the Bladder and the ſtreight Gut, which keep it from ſwaying or rowling, yet give it liberty to ſtretch and delate it ſelf, and again to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract as nature in that cauſe diſpoſes it: Its figure is in a manner round, and not unlike a Gourd, leſſening a little, and growing more acute toward one end the bottom, being knit together by its proper Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, its Neck likewiſe is joyn'd by its own ſubſtance, &amp; certain membranes that faſten it to <hi>Os Sacrum,</hi> and the Share-bone. As to its largeneſs that much differs in women, eſpecially the difference is great between ſuch as have born Children, and thoſe that have born none: In ſubſtance it is ſo thick that it exceeds a Thumbs breadth, which after Conception is ſo far from decreaſing that it augments to a greater proportion, and the more to ſtrengthen and confirm it, it is interwoven with Fibres overthwart ſtrait, and winding, and its proper Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are Veins, Arteries and Nerves, and amongſt theſe are two little Veins, which paſs from the Spermatick Veſſels to the bettom of the Womb, and two larger from the Hypogaſtricks, which viſit both the bottom and the Neck, the mouth of theſe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:56968:49"/>veins piercing as far as the inward conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, in which place the extremities of them are called <hi>Acetabula,</hi> which when the Courſes flow, open themſelves, and evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the eflux of Blood, and therefore they are the more conſpicuous in Women with Child, that part called the Liver of the Womb, being joyned to them the better to extract Blood for the Childs nouriſhment, at which time their veins do ſo ſwell eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially near their time of delivery, that they equal in bigneſs the Emulgent veins, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear half as thick as the hollow Veins.</p>
               <p>The Womb hath alſo two Arteries on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth ſides, the ſpermatick Veſſels and the Hypogaſticks, which ſtill attend or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the Veins, and beſides theſe there are divers little Nerves knit and intwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the form of a Net, which extend throughout, even from the bottom to the Privities themſelves, being chiefly placed for ſenſe and pleaſure, moving in Sympathy between the Head and the Womb.</p>
               <p>Now it is to be further noted, that by reaſon of two Ligaments that hang on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the Womb, from the ſhare-bone and piercing through the <hi>Peritonaeum,</hi> and are joyned to the bone it ſelf, that the Womb is movable upon ſundry occaſions, often ſalling low or riſing high; as for the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:56968:49"/>Neck of the Womb it is of an exquiſit feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo that if it be any time out of order, by being troubled with a ſchirous brawn, over-fatneſs, moiſture, or relaxation, the Womb is ſubjected thereby to Barrenneſs: In thoſe that are with Child there frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtayes a moſt glutenous matter in the enterance to facilitate the Birth; for at the time of delivery the mouth of the Womb is opened in a ſtrange manner, to ſuch a wideneſs as is conformable to the bigneſs of the Child, ſuffering an equal dilatation from the bottom to the top.</p>
               <p>As for the preparatory of Spermatick Veſſels in VVomen, they conſiſt of 2 veins, and 2 arteries, not differing from thoſe in a Man, but only in their largeneſs &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of inſertion; for, as for their number, there are ſo many Veins and the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Arteries as in men, the right vein iſſuing from the trunk of the hollow vein deſcending, &amp; the left from the Emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent vein, and on the ſide of them are two Arteries which grows from the <hi>Aorta,</hi> and bring vital Blood for the accompliſhment of the work of Generation.</p>
               <p>As to the Longitude and Latitude of theſe Veſſels, they are narrow, and ſhorter in women than in men; only obſerve where they are wrinkled or crumpled, they are
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:56968:50"/>more wreathed and contorted than in men, as ſhrinking together by reaſon of their ſhortneſs, they may by their looſneſs be the better ſtretched out, when occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it, and that by their drawing up as it were, the Blood might ſtay there in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er quantity for the preparation of the Seed. And theſe Veſſels in Women are carried with an oblique Courſe through the leſſer. Guts to the Teſticles or Stones, but are in the mid-way divided into two Branches, the greater going to the Stones, conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the various or winding Body, and wonderful Inoculation; the leſſer Branch ending in the Womb, in the ſide of which it diſperſeth it ſelf, and chiefly at the higher part of the bottom of the Womb, for the nouriſhment thereof, as alſo of the Child, and that part of the Courſes may purge through theſe Veſſels: and feeing the Stones in Women are ſeated near the Womb, for that cauſe theſe Veſſels fall not from the <hi>Peritonaeum,</hi> neither make they ſuch Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as in Men, nor extend themſelves to the Share-bone.</p>
               <p>The Stones in Women, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Teſticles, altho' they perform the ſame Action as mens, if rightly conſidered, yet are they different in their ſituation, magnitude, temperament, ſubſtance, form
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:56968:50"/>and covering. As for their ſeat it is in the hollowneſs of the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> neither are they Externally pendulous, but reſt upon the Muſcles of the Loyns, that ſo they may by contracting the greater heat be more Fruitful, their Office being to contract and elaborate that matter, which in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with Mans Seed ingenders Man, yet they differ from thoſe of Men in figure, by reaſon of their leſſneſs and flatneſs, at either end not being ſo round nor Oval. The external Superficies being likewiſe more unequal, appearing like the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of a great many knots and kernels mixed together, there is alſo another dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in their ſubſtance, they being much more ſoft and plyable, looſe, and not ſo well compacted.</p>
               <p>Their magnitude and temperament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo different, for they are much colder and leſſer than thoſe in Men, by reaſon of which a thinner and feebler Seed is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by one Sex then by the other; as for their covering or incloſure, it likewiſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers extreamly, for as Mens are wraped or covered in divers Tunicles, by reaſon they are externally Pendulous, and ſubject to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers injuries, unleſs ſo fenced by nature, ſo Womens Stones being internal and leſs ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to casualty, are covered with one Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:56968:51"/>or Membrane, the which though it cloſely adhere to them, yet are they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe half covered with the <hi>Peritonaeum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The different or Ejaculatory Veſſels, are two obſcure paſſages one on either ſide, nothing differing from the Spermatick veins in ſubſtance; riſe they do on one part from the bottom of the Womb, not reaching from their other extremity, either to the Stones, or any other part, but ſhut up and unpaſſable, adhearing to the Womb, as the Colon does to the blind Gut, and winding half way about; the Stones are every way remote to them, yet though they touch them not, they are tyed to them by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Membranes, reſembling the Wings of a Batt or Flutter-mouſe, through which certain Veins and Arteries paſſing from the Stones end, in theſe beginning, or may be termed here to have their paſſages, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the corners of the Womb to the Stones, and are accounted the proper Ligaments by which the Stones and the Womb are united, and ſtrongly knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and theſe Ligaments in Women, are the Cremeſters in Men: Of which I ſhall ſpeak more largely, when I come to deſcribe the Maſculine parts conducing to Generation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:56968:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> A Diſcourſe of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Action of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parts in Woman, appropriated to Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Externals, commonly called the Privy Member, re deſigned to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the great Orifice, and that to receive the Yard, and give paſſage to the Birth and Urin. The uſe of the Wings and Knobs like Mirtle-berries, are for the ſecurity of the internal parts, ſhutting the Orifice and Neck of the Bladder, and by their ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iing up cauſe Titulation and Defire in thoſe parts, and alſo to obſtruct the unvoluntary paſſage of the Urine.</p>
               <p>The Action of the Clytoris is like that of the Yard, <hi>viz.</hi> Erection, where Erection is for motion and attraction of the Seed.</p>
               <p>The action and the uſe of the Neck of the Womb is equal with that of the Yard, <hi>viz.</hi> Erection, occaſioned divers ways. Firſt, in caſe of Copulation it is erected and made ſtrait for the paſſage of the Yard to the Womb. Secondly, whilſt the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is repleated with Spirit and vital Blood, it becomes more ſtrait for embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:56968:52"/>the Yard: as for the conveniency of Erection it is twofold. Firſt, for as much as if the neck of the Womb was not erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Yard could have no convenient Paſſage to the Womb. Secondly, the Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation which occaſions the Seed to iſſue forth, could be no other ways: nay, to this we may add, that it hinders any hurt or damage that might enſue through the violent Concuſſion of the Yard during the time of Copulation.</p>
               <p>As for the Veſſels that paſs through the neck of the Womb, their Office is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat it with Blood and Spirit, that ſtill as the moiſture conſumes by the heat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted there in Copulation, it may by thoſe Veſſels be renewed, and the menſtruous Blood at unſeaſonable times, for its Efflux be kept back: nor are theſe all their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for they contribute Nutriment towards the Child when in the Womb.</p>
               <p>The Womb it ſelf has many properties attributed to it, as, Firſt Attraction of the Seed by Familiar Sympathy.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It retains it, which is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Conception.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It cheriſhes and changes the Seed, continuing ſo to do till it by the help of Nature frames the Child, and brings it to perfection, and then it ſtrongly operates
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:56968:52"/>in ſending forth the Birth when the time of its remaining there is expired, dilating and ſpreading it ſelf in a wonderful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and indeed is the Field of Mans Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, being deſigned for no other purpoſe, and ſo aptly removed from the Senſes, that nothing of Injury can proceed from thence retaining in it ſelf a power and ſtrength to operate and caſt forth the Birth, unleſs by accident or the like it be rendered de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient. When to ſtrengthen and inable it, beſides the helps of Nature, ſundry Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendies are to be applied by skilful hands Direction. For which ſhall be hereafter mentioned.</p>
               <p>The Utility of the preparing Veſſels are taken from their Original, and from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certion of the right vein, proceeding from the hallow, and the left from the emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent vein as in men, that hot and pure Blood may more abundantly flow: from the right vein for the Procreation of Males, and that ſerous and watery Blood may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the emulgent vein for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation of Females.</p>
               <p>The Veſſels in this kind are much ſhorter in Women than in Men, by reaſon of their nearneſs to the Stones, which defect is yet lengthened and made good, by the many Intricacies or Windings, to which thoſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:56968:53"/>Veſſels are ſubject, for in the middle way they derive themſelves into two branches, though different in magnitude, for one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greater than the other paſſes to the Stones conveying matter for compoſition of Seed, and the leſſer to the Womb, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering there ſuch Nutriment as it extracts from other parts of the Body; as for the Arteries, they afford the Blood which is more full of Spirit to perfect the Seed.</p>
               <p>The Stones in Women are greatly uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for where they are defective Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is at an end, by reaſon they operate in preparing the Seed, as thoſe in Men, and by reaſon the Woman is colder than the Man, therefore are they ſeated within, that they ſhould have the more heat to cheriſh them; and for that cauſe are they covered only with one Tunicle, that the heat may have the eaſier acceſs, though by reaſon of their ſoftneſs they cannot perfect ſo ſubſtantial a Seed as thoſe of Men, as being cheriſhed with leſs heat, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder might ſupply the inferiour parts.</p>
               <p>Their figure is not exactly round but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that the ſmall meanders of the veins diſperſed, through the Members, from the Stones to the different Veſſels, might have more room to be inſerted for the attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Seed, by the Subſtance of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:56968:53"/>Stones, the inequality contributing to the longer ſtay of the Seed in thoſe meandring Veſſels, nor is rugedneſs or unevenneſs of them leſs conducing thereto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of Conception, and the infallible Signs thereof; as alſo whether it be a Male or Female, that is conceived, or both at once, commonly called Twins.</head>
               <p>THE next thing convenient to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in this Treatiſe, and as it falls in courſe, is Conception and its Symptoms, very material and worthy of note, not only by Midwives, but all young Women. Now the ſigns of Conception 3 or 4 days after convenient and ſatisfactory Copulation, are</p>
               <p>Pains in the Head, Virtigo and dimneſs of the Eyes, the Aples of the Eyes decreaſe, the Eyes themſelves ſwell, and become of a dull or dark colour, their veins waxing red and ſhut with Blood: Again, if the Eyes ſink, the Eybrows grow looſe, various co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours appear in the Eyes, and little red
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:56968:54"/>Pimples ſuddainly ariſe in the Face, and almoſt as ſuddainly diſappear. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. if the Veins between the Eyes and Noſe are exteuded with Blood, the Veins under the Tongue look greeniſh, the Neck fluſheth with heat, the Back bone cold, the Veins and Arteries ſwell, and the Pulſes are obſerved more eaſily. Fourthly, If the Veins in the Breaſts appear blackiſh, and afterwards turn yellow, the Teats look firey, and upon drinking cold drink, the Woman feels it as it were in her Breaſts. Fifthly, if ſhe on a ſuddain fall to loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Meat and Drink, coveting things, unreaſonable and not fit for Suſtenance: be troubled with Pukeins, weakneſs of Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, ſore declining, and there be little Worms found about her Navel. Sixthly, If the lower part of the Belly ſwell, and weakneſs be contracted in her Loyns with inward Gripings and retention of the courſe 7 days after copulation: After which act, there is a Cold and Trembling ſeizes on the Members External, by reaſon the force of the Womb violently attracts the heat, &amp; dries up the moiſture. Seventhly, It is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſign of Conception, if the Midwife put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up her finger, find the interior neck of the Womb exactly cloſed. If the Womb wax round and ſwell, the Courſes ſtay, the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:56968:54"/>Thighs ſwell with ſome pain, the whole Body grows weak, the Face at times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Pale, the Urine white with a little cloud after ſome ſtanding at the top of it, if many Attoms appear in it. Eighthly, if Urine be put up in a Glaſs three days, and the Woman have conceived, certain live things will appear to ſtir in it: if a bright Needle be put in a whole night, and ſhe have conceived, divers little red Specks will be thereon, but if not it will be black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh or ruſty: nor are theſe Imaginations, but the approved Aſſertions of the Learned in Phyſick, and Skilful in Midwifry, who have made it their ſtudy to ſearch into the depth of Natures Secrets: And next comes a nicer Point to be treated of, not without the Patronage of ſuch, whoſe Wiſdom and indefatigable Labours have rendered them famous to Poſterity. The which take as followeth.</p>
               <p>After Conception, and the Child be come to ſome perfection, ſo that the Sex may be diſtinguiſhed, if it happen to be a Male Child, then the right Eye of the Woman will, to appearance, move ſwifter, and ſparkle more than the left: the right Pap will riſe, ſwell, and be more hard than the left, and the Teats colour will change more ſuddenly, and the increaſe of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:56968:55"/>Milk will be ſpeedy, and if it be milked out and ſet in the Sun, it will look like Pearl, contracting it ſelf into a more ſolid matter than ordinary; or if upon the milk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it out, you caſt it upon the Womans Urin, it will ſink to the bottom. Her right Cheek will often glow, and be more ruddy than the left, and indeed the whole colour of her Face more lively than at other times, ſhe feels leſs Sadneſs than if ſhe conceived a Female. And when firſt the Child ſtirs, it is more brisk and ſtrong in its motion than the other, having commonly its firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the right ſide on the ſixtieth day if her Courſes flow the fortieth day after Conception, if her Belly be more accute towards the Navel, and as ſhe goes ſhe puts her right Leg foremoſt, and riſing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to eaſe her ſelf on the right ſide more than on the left.</p>
               <p>Now in caſe a Female be conceived, the tokens are averſe to theſe for the moſt part, the firſt motion rarely happening before the 19th day after Conception, and then it is made on the left ſide. Females are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with more pains than Males, thro' de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of heat in the Womb to attract the ſubſtance, alſo the Thighs and Genital Members of the Woman ſwell more than ordinary, her Colour departs, and her
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:56968:55"/>Longings are Extream, and her Courſes flow the Thirtieth day after Conception.</p>
               <p>If Twins are conceived, which many times happens through the ſtrange diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Womb, and exceeding quantity of Seed, the ſign thereof will not appear till the third or fourth month after concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then the firſt appearance will be by the motion of the Infants both ways, that is, on either ſide of the Womb at once, for they receive their Souls at one and the ſame time; alſo if her two Flanks ſwell higher than the middle of the Belly; if there does appear a line, or as it were a diviſion from the Navel to the Groyn, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a kind of a Channel, or if the Woman with more than ordinary pain ſupport her burthen. And thus much may ſuffice for theſe, from whence I ſhall proceed to give the Reader an inſight into falſe Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that frequently deceive Women, eſpecially ſuch as are over deſirous of Children.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:56968:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of falſe Conceptions, and how to know them.</head>
               <p>HAving already treated of true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, the next thing note worthy is, what relates to falſe Conceptions, and in this caſe Women are ſometimes delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, thinking themſelves with Child, when their Belly only ſwell with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of their uſual Courſes that fall not according to their uſual times, or elſe by a lump of indigeſted Fleſh, for the moſt part like the Gizard of a Fowl, greater or leſſer, according to the time of its continuance there, which is frequently four months, and is called a Moon Calf.</p>
               <p>At other times they are deceived by Moles, which are twofold, <hi>viz.</hi> The true and a falſe, the former of which is a fleſhly body, filled with many Veſſels, ſtreaked with white, green, or black Lines, not deficent of Membranes, but incompaſſed with divers, yet without growth, motion, Bones, Bowels, or any Internals, receiving its nouriſhment through certain veins, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it lives, as we may ſay the life of a Plant, without any figure or order
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:56968:56"/>ingendered Original in the concavity of the Matrix adhearing to its ſide, but not participating of its ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>The latter of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the falſe Mole may be divided into four diſtinctions, as following. Firſt the windy Mole, being a contraction or conflux of wind. Secondly, the watery Mole being a gathering of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thirdly, the Humourous Mole, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux of divers humours; and Fourthly the Membranous Mole, being many Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes in the form of a Bag filled with Blood, and of theſe in their order.</p>
               <p>The Mole is contracted in the Womb, when a Woman has copulation, during her monthly Purgations, or otherways unſeaſonably, or elſe when ſhe lies with great deſire and luſt with her Husband, when ſhe has already conceived, or by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her Courſes beyond the time Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture allows for their expurgation.</p>
               <p>The windy Mole is occaſioned through defect of heat in the Womb and parts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent, as the Liver and Spleen, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender a polite or windy vapour, which fills the membranous parts, and puffs up the concavity of the Matrix.</p>
               <p>The watry Mole is ingendred of divers apt confluences of thin matter or watry Efluxes, which paſſing through the Veſſels,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:56968:57"/>evacuates into the Womb, having its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal from the Spleen, Liver, or parts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning, and above all from the Liver, when 'tis cold, weak, and not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct all the Nutriment into Blood, ſo that the remainder turning into watey humour falls into the Womb, and cannot be eaſily voided thence.</p>
               <p>The Humorous Mole is ingendered by moiſt attracted humours, as the Whites or certain watery Purgations, which diſtill from the Menſtruous Veins, and gathering into a glutenous ſubſtance, ſtay in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavity of the womb.</p>
               <p>The Membranous Mole is no other then a contraction of Blood within a Skin or Membrane, to which is faſtned many white and tranſparent Veſſels filled with Blood, the which coming forth, and being thrown into Water, the Blood goes out, and the Membrane rumbles together, ſhrinking on a heap like coagulated Seed.</p>
               <p>Now moſt or all of theſe falſe conceptions have many ſigns or ſymptoms, coherent with the true, as the depravity of Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, puking, ſwelling, ſuppreſſion of the Courſes, ſwelling of the Breaſts and Belly, ſo that many are at a plunge to diſtinguiſh them; for indeed it is moſt eaſily to be done, though in theſe following matters
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:56968:57"/>there is diſtinction, <hi>viz.</hi> In caſe of a falſe Conception the Breaſt ſwell, and fall again not containing any Milk, the Face is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently puffed up, the Arms, the Groyn, and the Thighs, grow megat and lanker, the Belly waxes hard, as if Dropſical, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt of an equal roundneſs, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prickings at the bottom, ſcarcely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of Intermiſſion, which breaks the reſt of the Women ſo afflicted; divers other ſigns are there to know it by, eſpecially the true or fleſhy Mole; as thus, A Male In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant begins to move at the beginning of the third month for the moſt part, and the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male at the end of the third or beginning of the fourth: now when any motion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, the Women ought to conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe have any Milk in her breaſts; if ſhe have, it is a ſign of a true Coneption, but the contrary, of a falſe one: it is alſo the ſign of a true Conception, if the Child move freely and lively in all parts of the Womb, for although there is a motion in a falſe Conception, yet it is dull, and not quick nor active in motion, the motion not being in it ſelf but in the expulſive Faculty of the Mother: and further, if the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man obſerve, ſhe may perceive it fall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to the ſide ſhe lies on, and ſhe lying on her back, if her belly be ſtroked down,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:56968:58"/>the burden will deſcend, and not have for want of inbred force a power to recover its Station. But what confirms it more is, that 9 Months expired no Travel enſues, but her Belly ſtill increaſes, whilſt all the reſt of the body grows lean, and out of order.</p>
               <p>The Signs of the windy Mole are divers, as the ſudden ſtretching of the Belly like a bladder, yet ſoft and ſpungy, eſpecially near the Groins, and ſmall thereof, when if it be ſtruck it ſounds like a drum, and that the Swelling is ſometimes more, and ſometimes leſs, ſo that according to its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or decreaſe, the Woman feels more heavy or more light.</p>
               <p>The watery Mole is known by its di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtention of the Belly, and eſpecially when ſhe lies upon her back, the ſides thereof are more ſwelled than the middle or the bottom, which grows flatter by reaſon the watery Humour falls to the ſides, moving up and down, as if it were a fluctuation of Water, and much to the ſame purpoſe as the Symptoms of the humorous Mole, only with this diſtinction, that the Flanks and Thighs are more ſtretched by the Wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mole than by the other, becauſe the Water being thinner than the Humour, or not confined in Cells, flows thither, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:56968:58"/>that which in caſe of a watry Mole comes through Natures conduite is clear, when in caſe of a humourous Mole, the water is red or of a bloody colour.</p>
               <p>Further obſerve, in caſe of a falſe concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Courſes come not down, and the Navel of the Mother advanceth it ſelf little or nothing; which in true Conception is otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Other falſe Conceptions there are occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by divers Tumours, which the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant take for Moles, when they are only Rotundies and ſwelling the Belly, which are not diſcovered till the Womb be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and then though the Womb be not all out of order, there does appear at one or both corners thereof little bags full of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in others there are to be ſeen a heap of Kernels, or ſuperfluous fleſh, like a cluſter of Grapes in the Womb, cauſing it to ſwell. Yet in ſuch caſes, the Courſes are obſerved to proceed in due order, which denotes the Womb to be in good order.</p>
               <p>Another Excreſcency of Fleſh there is which ſome call a Pendent Mole, being a piece of fleſhy ſubſtance, hanging within the Interior Neck of the Womb, being in breadth about a finger at the place where it is faſtned, increaſing bigger and bigger towards the bottom like a ſmall Bell, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:56968:59"/>the whole Orifice of the privy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſometimes appearing outward to a great bigneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Inſtructions for Women how to govern themſelves, during their being with Child.</head>
               <p>THeſe Inſtructions being exceeding neceſſary, I thought fit to lay them down for a Rule to ſuch as are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of ſelf-preſervation. And indeed for want of due obſervance, divers Diſeaſes afflict Child-bearing Women; nay the Child is frequently loſt, or if it come to a perfect Birth, proves ſickly and diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the evil Humours that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to it, through the Mothers miſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, then the Woman with Child ought to chooſe a Temperate Air, not infected with Fogs ariſing from Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Ditches, Ponds, Lakes, or Rivers, and not to go abroad in too hot, nor too cold weather, nor when the South wind blows ſtrong; for that wind above all
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:56968:59"/>others, diſturbs and diſorders Women with Child, oftentimes cauſing Abortion: And next to it the North-wind is hurtful, cauſing Catarrhs, Coughs, and Rhumes, which opening the body, cauſes the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to bring forth before her time. In ſhort, if any evil Vapour be drawn in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring pregnancy, cauſes divers Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>In caſe of Diet, ſhe ought to be very cautious in chuſing ſuch Meats as create wholſome Nouriſhment, all Meats that are moderately dry being taken ſo to do; and let her obſerve not to faſt immoderately, for that renders the Child ſickly and weak, and often for want of Nouriſhment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains it to be born before its time; nor on the other hand, muſt ſhe be too glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonous, for that again ſtuffs it, and cauſes it to ſwell beyond its natural bounds.</p>
               <p>All Meats either too hot or too cold, and moiſt, are to be avoided, as Salads, Spices, Meats, and the extraordinary uſe of her Meats, which makes the Children come forth oftentimes without Nails, which is a ſign of ſhort life. The moſt wholſome Meats in this caſe are Pidgeons, Turtles, Larks, Partridges, Pheaſants, Veal, Mutton, or any ſuch Meats that is of good Juice, and contributing to kindly Nouriſhment, as alſo ſuch Fruits as are ſweet and often
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:56968:60"/>digeſtion, as Cherries, Pears, Damſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but let her avoid ſuch things as ſubject her Body to windineſs</p>
               <p>Her Longings, if Extravagant, ſhe muſt reſtrain, at leaſt as much as in her lies, not eating any thing that is filthy or contrary to nouriſhment, nor let her ſleep immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after Meals, and not at all in the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time if ſhe can avoid it; the Night being preferable in ſuch caſes, when ſhe may ſleep her fill, ſo it exceed not 9 hours.</p>
               <p>Her Exerciſe ought to be moderate: for violent motion, either in walking or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, looſens the <hi>Cylendons</hi> through which the Child receives its Nouriſhment, riding in a Coach, eſpecially upon the Stones, or in uneven way (the laſt three Months is dangerous) as alſo extraordinary Sounds, Noiſes, and above all the Ringing of the Bells, and diſcharging the Guns.</p>
               <p>Laughing, Crying, or immoderate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or any other Paſſion, is extreamly hurtful; nor in the firſt four Months after Conception ought ſhe to lye with her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, for as much as the Act of Copulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on moves and ſhakes the Womb, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Fruit therein cauſes the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to deſcend. She muſt likewiſe in the 6th and 8th Month abſtain; but in the 7th and 9th it is not forbidden, but rather
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:56968:60"/>to be encouraged, by reaſon as Phyſicians affirm, it opens the paſſage, and thereby fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitates the Birth: and the better to help it, the Woman ought to take ſuch things as may keep her Body ſoluble, as Syrups and other looſening matters, as may help Nature in its operation; eſpecially let her obſerve when ſhe grows any thing big, to lay aſide her busk, and go looſe, that the Child may have free Scope, for two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt, that it may not be hurt: and ſecondly, that being unreſtrained, it may come to its full growth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Further Conſiderations how Women ought to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern themſelves during Pregnancy.</head>
               <p>TIS further to be obſerved, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter delivery the Breaſts frequently grow extream large, and ſwell over much, to prevent which (and to avoid the danger of too much Blood, which cauſe curdled or curdy Milk, ſo that from the effects thereof divers Diſeaſes ariſe in the Breaſt) ſo ſoon as the Woman perceives
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:56968:61"/>her ſelf with Child, let her wear about the Neck a ſmall Necklace of Gold or Steel, or a ſmall ingot of the latter, to hang be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her two Breaſts, ſomenting her Breaſts a quarter of an hour every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Water diſtilled from Sage, Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winkle, art ground-Ivy, being blood-warm.</p>
               <p>In her fourth month, when the motion is great, and her belly ſeells big, ſhe may ſwath it with a Swath-band, anointed with <hi>Pomatum,</hi> or the like, to make which I ſhall give direction, and in ſo doing ſhe will keep it ſmooth, and free from wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, as alſo from hanging down like a Trip after delivery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Receipt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the Gall of Kid, and of a Sow, of each 3 ounces, of Capons greaſe, and Gooſe greaſe, of each one ounce and a half, and having melted them, put thereto a quarter of a pint of water, after which ſtrain them through a Linnen Cloath into fair water, caſting it to and fro therein till it be white, at what time add to it the marrow of a red Deet, one ounce, and lay it in red Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water 12 hours, after the expiration of which you may uſe it in anointing the Swath as aforeſaid, as alſo the Belly.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:56968:61"/>
               <p>If the Ingredients aforeſaid cannot be gotten, then the following Linnament is effectual, though the former is better, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Make of Mutton Suet adjoying to the Kidneys, and of Dogs Greaſe, each two ouces, Whale Oyl, an ounce, and of ſweet Almon Oyl, the like quantity, waſh them well after they are melted together in the water of Germander, or new White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine, and anoit the Belly therewith, or the Swath band ordained to ſupport it. But for ſuch as are not deſirous to anoint their Bellies, they may uſe the following Bath or Concoction.</p>
               <p>Take of all the ſorts of Mallows, and of Motherwort, each two handfuls, Lilly-roots, the white ones, to the weight of 3 ounces, Melilot and Chammomile, of both two handfuls, Lime-ſeed, Quince-ſeed and Feen-greek ſeed, 3 ounces proportionable of each, concoct them in Spring-water, and bath therewith.</p>
               <p>If the Woman during her pregnancy feels but little motion in her Womb, let her make a quilt as followeth, and bind it upon her Navel, and it will greatly ſtrengthen the Infant, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the powder of Roſes, red Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Gillyflowers, of each 3 ounces, Maſtick a dram, and of Augelica ſeeds two
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:56968:62"/>drams, two grains of Ambergreaſe, and one of Musk, all which being well beaten, put them into a Linnen bag, expanded and quilted that they may be in every part of it, placing it upon the Navel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Rules to he obſerved upon a Woman lying down, and her delivery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving thus far proceed, in what as I highly conceived is neceſſary to be known by the Profeſſors of this Art. I ſhall Gradually proceed to what remains: And firſt to inform the Reader what is neceſſary to be obſerved upon a Womans lying in order to her delivery.</p>
               <p>The hour, according to computation of time, and the diſpoſition of the Body ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, let the Woman ſend for a skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Midwife not delaying ſo to do, but rather too ſoon than too late; at what time let her prepare a little Bed or Couch of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate height, and ſo ſituate that it be far from the Door, near the Fire, and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieut for the Midwife and her aſſiſtants to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:56968:62"/>paſs round, and be aiding on every ſide as occaſion requires, having change of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, and a ſmall Cricket, or little Log of Timber to reſt her feet againſt, ſhe having more force when they are bowed, than otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Having thus provided, when the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man find her Pains come on, if the weather he not extream cold, let her walk leiſurely about the Room, reſting her ſelf by turns upon the Bed, expecting ſo the coming down of her Water, which is a Humour that is contracted in one of the outward Membranes, and flows thence when it is broke by the ſtrugling of the Child, or ſome other accident, there being no direct time affixed for its Efflux, though for the moſt part it flows not above two hours before the Birth. Motion likewiſe will cauſe the Womb to open and dilate it ſelf, when lying long in Bed will prove troubleſome, yet if ſhe be much ſpent and weakened, ſhe may take ſome gentle Cordial to refreſh her ſelf, if her pains will permit it.</p>
               <p>If her Travel be tedious, to revive her Spirits ſhe may take any broath of Chikens or Mutton, and after it a poached Egg, but muſt not take any thing to exceſs. As for the Poſtures Women are delivered in, they are divers, ſome laying in their beds, others
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:56968:63"/>ſiting in a Chair, ſupported and held by others, or reſting upon the ſide of the Bed or Chair; ſome again upon the Knees, being ſupported under their Arms; but the ſafeſt and moſt commodious way is in the Bed, when as the Midwife ought to obſerve theſe following Rules.</p>
               <p>Let her ſee that the Woman be layed upon her Back, her head a little elevated by the help of a Pillow, having the like help to ſupport her Reins and Buttocks, and that her Rump lye high; for if ſhe lye low, ſhe cannot be well delivered, then let her keep her Knees and Thighs as far aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as ſhe can, her Legs bowed together, her Buttocks, the Soles of her Feet and Heels being fixed upon a Little Log of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber placed for that purpoſe, that ſhe may have the greater force to ſtrain: now in caſe her Back be exceeding weak, a Swath-band may be caſt under it, the band being four double, and about 12 inches broad, and this muſt be held by two perſons, who with ſteady hands and equal motion muſt raiſe her up at the time the Pains happen; but if they be not exact in their motion 'tis better evaded: and at the ſame time let 2 Women hold her Shoulders, that ſhe may the better ſtrain out the Birth with more advantage, and the better to facilitate it,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:56968:63"/>let a Woman ſtroak or preſs the upper part of her Belly gently, and by degrees, nor muſt the Woman her ſelf be faint hearted, but Couragious, and of a good Heart, forcing her ſelf by ſtraining and ſtopping her Breath.</p>
               <p>In caſe of Delivery, the Midwife muſt wait with patience, till the Childs Head or othre Members burſt the Membrane; for if through Ignorance, or haſt to be gone to other Woman, a sſome have done; the Midwife tear the Membranes with her Nails, ſhe indangers both the woman and the Child, for it lying dry, and wanting that ſlipperyneſs that ſhould facilitate it, its ligreſs comes forth with greater Pain.</p>
               <p>When the Head appears, the Midwife muſt gently hold it between her two hands, and draw the Child at ſuch times as the Womans pangs are upon her, and at no other, ſlipping by degrees her four fingers under its Armpits, not uſing a rough hand in drawing it forth, leaſt by ſuch means the Child through its tenderneſs, receive any deformity of Body.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Child is taken forth, which is commonly with its Face down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, let it be laid upon its Back, that it may more freely receive external Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:56968:64"/>then cut the Navel-ſtring with a a ſharp Inſtrument about three inches from the Body, tying that which adheres to the Belly with a Silken ſtring as near as you can, then cover the Head and Stomach of the Child well, ſuffering nothing to come upon the Face.</p>
               <p>The Child being thus drawn forth, and in Health, lay it aſide, and let the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife regard the Patient, in drawing or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to come forth the Secundine, which are the contracted Membranes: And this may be done by wagging and ſtirring them up and down, and afterward with a gentle hand drawing them forth, or if the work be difficult, let the Woman hold Salt in her hands, ſhut them cloſe, and breath hard into them, whereby ſhe ſhall know whether the ſaid Membranes are broken or not: The like may be known by cauſing a ſtrain, or Vomiting, by putting one Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger down her Throat, by ſtraining or moving her Inferior parts, being all obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be done out of hand. If this fail, ſhe may take a draught of raw Elder wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the Yolk of a raw Egg, or ſmell to a piece of <hi>Fſſa-Faetida,</hi> eſpecially if ſhe be troubled with the Wind chollick; a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for which I ſhall hereafter preſcribe. If ſhe have taken Cold, it is a great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:56968:64"/>to the coming down of the Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines; and in ſuch caſes the MIdwife ought to chaſe the Womans Belly with a gentle hand, which breaks not only the wind, but obliges the Secondine to come down: And theſe proving Ineffectual, the Midwife muſt dilate with her hand the exterior Orifice of the Womb, and gently draw it forth. Having diſcourſed of common Births, or ſuch as for the moſt part are eaſie, I ſhall proceed to give directions in caſe of Extremity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> In caſe of Extremity, what ought to be Obſerved, eſpecially to Women who in their Travel, are accompanied with an Eflux of Blood, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions or Fits of the Wind.</head>
               <p>IN caſe of Extremity, greater regard muſt be had then at other times, and firſt of al the ſituation of the Womb, and her poſture of lying muſt be croſs the Bed, being held by ſuch as have ſtrength to prevent her ſliping down, or moving her ſelf in the operation of the Man Midwife, or Chirurgeon, her Thighs muſt be ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as wide as may be, and ſo held whilſt her Legs invert or bend backward
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:56968:65"/>towards her Hips, her Head leaning upon a Bolſter, and the Reins of her Back ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the like, nor Rump and Buttocks likewiſe Elevated, obſerving to cover her Stomack, Belly, and Thighs with warm Linnen, to keep them from cold winds.</p>
               <p>The woman being in the poſture afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, let the Operator put up his hand, if he finds the neck of the Womb dilated, and remove the contracted Blood that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs the paſſage of the Birth, and having by degrees with much gentleneſs made way, let him tenderly move the Infant, his hand being firſt anointed with ſweet Butter, or a harmleſs Pomatum; and if the waters are not come down, then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any difficulty may they be let forth, when if the Infant attempts to break forth with the Head foremoſt or croſs, he may gently turn it to find the Feet, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done, let him draw forth one, and faſten to it a Ribbon, then put it up again, and by degree find the other, when bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as cloſe and even as may be, and between whiles giving the Woman leave to breath, urging her to ſtrain in helping Nature to perfect the Birth, he may draw it forth, and the better to do it, that his hold may be the ſurer, he muſt faſten or wrap a Linen Cloath about the Childs
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:56968:65"/>Thighs obſerving to bring it into the World with its Face downward.</p>
               <p>In caſe of a flux of Blood, if the Neck of the Womb be open, it muſt then be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely conſidered, whether the Infant or the Secundines come firſt, which often the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter happening to do, ſtop the mouth of the Womb and hinder the Birth, to the endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering both the Woman and the Child; in ſuch a caſe, I ſay, the Secundine muſt be removed by a ſwift turn, and indeed they have by their ſo coming down deceived many, who feeling their ſoftneſs, ſuppoſed the Womb was not delated, and by their being ſo decived, the Woman and Child or at leaſt the latter, has been loſt, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundines removed, the Child muſt be ſought for, and drawed forth as has been directed, and if in ſuch a caſe the Woman or Child dye, the Midwife or Chirurgeon is blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs becauſe they did their true endeavour.</p>
               <p>If it appear upon enquiry that the Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine comes firſt, let the Woman be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with all convenient expedition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe great flux of Blood will follow, for then the Veins are opened, and upon this account two things are to be conſidered. Firſt the great or leſſneſs of the Secundines advancing, if the former and the head of the Child appear firſt, it muſt be guided
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:56968:66"/>and directed towards the Neck of the Womb, as in caſe of natural Births, but if there, thro' the weakneſs of the Child or Mother, appear any difficulty in the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, the beſt way is to ſearch for the feet, and thereby draw it forth; but if the latter, the Secundines may be put back with a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hand, and the Child firſt taken forth.</p>
               <p>Another matter is note worthy, <hi>viz.</hi> If the Secundines be far advanced, ſo that it cannot be put back, and the Child follow it cloſe, then are the Secundines to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken forth with much care, as ſwift as may be, and laid aſide without cutting the entrail that is faſtened to them, for by that you may be guided to the Infant, the which whether alive or dead muſt be drawn forth by the Feet with all expedition; tho' it is not to be acted unleſs in caſe of great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, for in other caſes the Secundine ought to come laſt.</p>
               <p>As for a dead Child, in drawing it forth let theſe Directions be carefully obſerved by the Chirurgion, <hi>viz.</hi> If the Child be found dead with its head foremoſt, the danger is the greater, and more difficult will be the Delivery; for it is an apparent ſign the Womans ſtrength begins to fail her, and that the Child being dead and wanting its inbred forced, can be no ways aſſiſted to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:56968:66"/>its delivery; wherefore the moſt certain and ſafe way is, for the Chirurgeon to put up his left hand, ſliding it as hollow in the Palm as he can into the neck of the Womb into the lower part thereof, towards the Feet, and that between the Head of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, and the Neck of the Matrix, when having a Hook in the right-hand couch it cloſe, and ſlit it up above the left-hand, between the Head of the Child, and the flat of his hand, fixing in it the bone of the Temple towards the Ear, or elſe in the hollow of the Eye, or for want of conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently coming at theſe in the occipital Bone, obſerving ſtill to keep the left hand in its place, with it gently moving and ſtirring the Head, and ſo with the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand and Hook draw the Child forward, admoniſhing the Woman to put forth her utmoſt ſtrength, ſtill drawing when the Womans pangs are upon her. The Head being drawn forth, he muſt with al ſpeed ſlip his hand under the Arm-holes of the Child, and take it quite forth, giving theſe things to the Woman, <hi>viz.</hi> A toſte of fine Wheat bread, in a quarter of a pint of Ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſs Wine.</p>
               <p>Now the former Application and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour failing, and the following Medicines will not inable the, Woman to caſt forth
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:56968:67"/>the Birth, you may proceed to Inſtruments after another manner. Firſt, when the Woman is in her bed, let her receive the inſuing potion hot, abſtaining from all manner of Meats, and reſt till ſhe feel the Operation; which is this.</p>
               <p>Take blue Figs to the number of 7, cut them in pieces, adding to them Fenegreek, Mother-wort, and Seeds of Rue, of each 2 Drams, water of Peneroyal and Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort 6 ounces of each, boyl them till one half be conſumed, and having ſtrained them again, and Trochiſchs of Mirrh a dra, and of Saffron 3 Grains, ſweetning the Liquor with Loaf-ſugar, and ſpicing it with Cinnamon.</p>
               <p>Having reſted upon this, let her labour again as much as may be; and if ſhe be not yet ſucceſsful, make a Suffumation of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, Oppoponax, Sulpher,</hi> and <hi>Aſſa Faetida,</hi> of each half a Dram, beating them into Powder, and wetting them with the juice of Rue till they become ſtiff, then burn them upon Coals, ſo that the Smoak or Fume may only come to the Matrix, and no further.</p>
               <p>If theſe effect not your deſire, then this Emplaiſter is very fitly to be applied, <hi>viz.</hi> Take of Galbanum one ounce and a half, Colocynthis without Grains 2 drams, the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:56968:67"/>juice of Motherwort and Rue, of each half an ounce, and 2 ounces of Virgin Bees-wax, bruiſe and melt them together, ſpreading them as a Scere cloath, to reach from the Navel to <hi>Os Pubis,</hi> ſpreading likewiſe to the flanks at the ſame time, making a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient peſſary of Wooll, cloſing it in a bag of Silk, and dipping it in the concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on round Birthworth, Savin, Colocyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this with Graines, Staves Acar, black Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore, of each a dram, and of Rue a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſprig or two.</p>
               <p>Theſe things failing, and the Womans life in danger, let the Chirurgeon uſe his Inſtruments to dilate and widen the Womb, to which purpoſe the Woman muſt be ſet in a Chair, ſo that ſhe may turn her Crup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as much from its back as is convenient, drawing up her Legs as cloſe as ſhe can, but ſpreading her Thighs as wide as may be, or if through her weakneſs it appear more convenient that ſhe be laid upon the Bed, with her Head downwards, her Buttocks raiſed, and her Legs drawn up as much as can be, a what time the Chirurgeon with his <hi>Speculum Matricis,</hi> or his Apertory, may dilate or widen the Womb, and draw out the Child and the Secundines together if it be poſſible, after which the Womb muſt be well waſhed and anointed, and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:56968:68"/>laid in her Bed, comforted there with Spices, pleaſant Meats and Cordials: This courſe muſt be taken in the delivery of all dead Children, likewiſe with Moles, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundines; or otherwiſe falſe Births, that will not of themſelves come forth in due ſeaſon, or if the Inſtruments aforeſaid will not ſufficient widen the Womb, then other Inſtruments, as the Drakes Bill, and long Pincers ought to be uſed.</p>
               <p>If it ſo happen that any Inflamation, Swelling, or concreet Blood be contracted in the <hi>perputium</hi> of the Matrix, under the Film of thoſe Tumours, either before or after the Birth, where the matter appears thinner, the Midwife with a Pen-knife, or inciſion Inſtrument may Lance it, and preſs out the corruption, healing it with a Peſſary dipped in Oyl of Red Roſes.</p>
               <p>If at any time through cold or ſome violence, the Child happens to be ſwelled in any part, or have contracted a watry Tumour; yet if it remain alive, ſuch means ought to be uſed as are leaſt inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the Child, or Mother, but if it be dead, that Tumour muſt be let out by inciſion to facilitate the Birth.</p>
               <p>It often happens that Children come with their Feet foremoſt, and the Hands dilating themſelves forth the Hips, in ſuch
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:56968:68"/>a caſe the Midwife muſt be well provided of neceſſary Oyntments to ſtroke &amp; anoint the Infant with, thereby to help its coming forth, leſt it return again into the Womb before it can be drawn forth, holding at the ſame time both the Arms of the Infant cloſe to the Hips, that ſo the Child may iſſue forth after its own manner, but if then it prove too big, then the Womb muſt be well anointed. The Woman may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take ſneezing powder, to cauſe her the more to ſtrain, and at the ſame time, thoſe that attend may gently ſtroke down her Belly, to make the Birth deſcend, and keep the Child when advanced, from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring back.</p>
               <p>Sometimes it falls out that the Child coming with its Feet foremoſt, has its ARms exended above its Head, the which ſo happening the Midwife muſt not receive it in that poſture, but put it back into the Womb, unleſs the paſſage be Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wide, and then ſhe muſt anoint both the Child and the womb, nor is it ſafe to draw it forth before it is put into due form, which muſt be done after this manner. The Woman lying upon her Back, with her Head depreſſed, and her Buttocks elevated, the Midwife with a gentle hand, muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Belly of the Woman towards the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:56968:69"/>Midrif, by that means to put back the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, obſerving to turn the Face of the Child towards the back of the Mother, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up its Thighs and Buttocks towards her Navel, thereby to bring it to a more regular and natural production.</p>
               <p>If a Child happen to come forth with one Foot, the Arm beign extended along the ſide, and the other Foot turned back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, then muſt the Woman be inſtantly brought to her bed, and laid in the poſture aforeſaid, at what time the Midwife muſt carefully put back the Foot ſo appearing, and the Woman rock her ſelf from one ſide to the other, till ſhe find the Child is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ſhe muſt not alter her poſture, nor turn upon her Face, after which ſhe may expect lier pains, and muſt have great aſſiſtance, Cordials eſpecially not being wanting to revive and ſupport her Spirits.</p>
               <p>At other times it ſo comes to paſs, that the Child lies croſs in the Womb and falls upon its ſide; if ſo it happen, the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muſt not be urged in her Labour, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any expect the Birth in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Therefore the Midwife when ſhe ſo perceives it, m uſt uſe great diligence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it to its right form, or ſuch a form in the Womb, as tis poſſible to deliver it; eſpecially by moving the Buttocks and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:56968:69"/>guiding the Head to the paſſage; but if ſhe be ſucceſsful herein, let her again try by rocking her ſelf too and fro, and wait with patience till it changes its manner of lying.</p>
               <p>Sometimes it falls out that the Child ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens to the Birth with the Legs and Arms diſtorted or expanded, in which, as in the former, the Woman muſt rock her ſelf, but not with any violence, till ſhe find the Legs and Arms fall to their proper ſtations; or it may be done by a gentle compreſſion of the Womb: but if neither of them prevail, the Midwife with her hand muſt cloſe the Legs of the Infant, and if poſſible ſhe can reach them, do the like to the Arms, and ſo draw it forth, though if it could be reduced of it ſelf to the compoſure or poſture of a natural Birth, it is better.</p>
               <p>If the Infant come forward with both Knees foremoſt, the Hands hanging down upon the Thighs, then muſt the Midwife put both Knees upward till the Feet appear, taking hold of which with her left hand, let her keep her right hand on the ſide of the Child, and in that poſture endeavour to bring it forth; but if ſhe cannot, then muſt the Woman rock her ſelf till the Child is in a more convenient poſture for Delivery.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:56968:70"/>
               <p>When it happens that the Child preſſes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with one Arm extended upon the Thighs, and the other elevated over his Head, the Feet likewiſe ſtretched out at length in the Womb, the Midwife in ſuch a poſture muſt not attempt to receive the Child, but muſt lay the Woman upon the bed in the manner often before recited, making a ſoft and gentle compreſſion upon her Belly to oblige the Infant to retire: and if of its own accord it retire not, then muſt the Midwife thruſt it back by the Shoulders, and bring the Arm that was ſtretched above the Head to its right place, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> certain it is the moſt dangerous in theſe Lxtremities: in this therefore the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife ought to take more care herein than ordinary; and firſt, ſhe muſt obſerve well to anoint her Hands, then the Womb of the Woman, either with ſome ſweet But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or ſome convenient <hi>Pomotum,</hi> thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up her hand as near as ſhe can to the Arm of the Infant, and reduce it to the ſide: but if ſhe cannot recall it, then muſt the Woman be laid on her bed, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for a while, and then again conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a Seat prepared for the moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency in that affair, by which time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Child may be reduced to a better poſture; the which when the Midwife
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:56968:70"/>finds, ſhe m uſt draw the Arms cloſe to the Hips, and ſo receive it.</p>
               <p>If an Infant came with its Buttocks fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, being in manner double, then the Midwife anointing her Hand, muſt thruſt it up, and by degrees by heaving the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks, and after them the Back, ſtrive to turn the Head to the paſſage, but be not over-haſty in ſo doing, leſt the Infant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring ſhould ſhape it ſelf worſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if it cannot be turned with the hand, the Woman muſt to Bed, and rock her ſelf, taking ſuch comfortable things as may ſupport her Spirits till ſhe perceive the Child turn.</p>
               <p>If a Child come foreward with its Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the Neck being bowed as it often happens, as alſo the Hands and Feet ſtretched upwards: In ſuch a caſe the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife muſt with much diligence move the Shoulders, that ſhe may direct the Head to the paſſage; and the better to perfect it, the Woman muſt rock her ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like methods are to be obſerved in all ſingle Births: And the ſame may be obſerved in caſe of Twins, or Trebble Births, for as the ſingle Birth has but one Natural way and many unnatural forms, even ſo it happens with the Birth of many Children, wherefore the Midwife muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:56968:71"/>(if Twins be in the Womb and preſs forward, according to the Natural form) that ſhe receive that firſt which is neareſt the paſſage, not letting the other go, leſt by retiring it ſhould change the form, nor muſt ſhe when one is born delay to bring forth the other; and this Birth in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural form is more eaſie, becauſe the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are moſt commonly leſs than the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle births, and conſequently require a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer paſſage; but if this Birth happen in an unnatural form, it is more difficult and dangerous. In the birth of Twins let the Midwiſe be exceeding careful that the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundine be naturally brought forth, leſt in ſuch a caſe the Womb being delivered of its burthen fall, and by its ſo doing the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundine continues there longer than is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, to the indangering of the Woman.</p>
               <p>If ſo it happen that the Womb is preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Twins, and one come naturally, and the other unnaturally, as the one with the Head, the other with the Feet fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, then muſt the Midwiſe conſider to deliver the natural birth firſt, and then if ſhe cannot turn the other, draw it out in the poſture it preſſes forward, but if that with the Feet downward be much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other, then may ſhe deliver that firſt, turning the Head of the other aſide.</p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:56968:71"/>
               <p>In this caſe the Midwiſe muſt be diligent to ſearch, that inſtead of Twins, it be not a monſterous Birth; as a Body with two Heads, or two bodies joyned together, which ſhe may obſerve if both the heads come foremoſt, by putting up her hands between them as high as ſhe can: and if ſhe find they are Twins, ſhe muſt gently put one of them aſide to make way for the other, taking that firſt that is moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, having regard to the other, that ſhe change not its ſituation.</p>
               <p>Now to prevent the firſt Child's being in danger of its Life, the Midwife, aſſoon as 'tis come forth, muſt tye the Navel-ſtring, as has been before directed, and alſo bind it again with a large and long Fillet, that part of the Navel that is faſtened to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundines, the more readily to find them. The Second Infant born, let her diligently it quire whether there be not two Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, for by the ſhortneſs of the Ligament it often happens that it retires back, to the damage of the Woman: wherefore, leſt in ſuch a caſe the Womb ſhould cloſe, it is moſt expedient to haſten them forth with all convenient ſpeed.</p>
               <p>If two Infants are joyned together by the body. as ſometimes monſtrouſly falls out, then although the Heads comes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:56968:72"/>yet is it convenient if poſſible to turn them, and draw them forth by the feet, obſerving when they come to the Hips to draw them forth as ſwift as may be: and in this caſe great care ought to be obſerved in anointing and widening the paſſage. And thus much for Extremity or Unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral-births, and the next thing I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to, is how to order the Woman after Natural or Unnatural Births, or Delivery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> What ought to be obſerved after Delivery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PReſently after Delivery, in caſe of a Natural Birth, eſpecially if the Woman has had hard labour, it is convenient to wrap her in the Skin of a Sheep taken off before it is cold, putting the fleſhy ſide to her Reins and Belly, or for want of this, the Skin of a Hare or Coney, being flayed off as ſoon as killed, may be applied to her Belly: and in ſo doing, the dilatation made in the Birth will be cloſed up, and the ill melancholy Blood expelled from thoſe parts: And theſe
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:56968:72"/>may be continued in Summer the ſpace of an hour, and in VVinter two; after which let the Woman be ſwathed with a fine linnen Cloth about a quarter of a Yard in length, chafing her Belly before with Oyl of St. <hi>Jahuſwort,</hi> after that raiſe up the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix with a linnen Cloath many times ſolded, then with a little Pillow or Quilt cover her Flanks, then uſe the Swath ſomewhat above the Hanches, winding it pretty ſtiff, applying at the ſame time a warm cloth to her Nipples, not preſently applying remedies to drive back the Milk, by reaſon the body at ſuch a time is diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and as it were out of frame, for there is neither Vein nor Artery which does not ſtrongly impulſe, where ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies as drive back the Milk being all of a diſſolving Nature, it is improper to apply them to the Breaſt during ſuch confuſion and diſorder, leſt by ſo doing evil Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours be ſtayed or contracted into the Breaſt; wherefore 12 hours ought to be the leaſt ſpace allowed for the Circulation and Settlement of the Blood, and what was caſt upon the Lungs by the vehement Agitation during the Labour, to retire to its proper Recepticles.</p>
               <p>A while after Delivery you make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive of the Yolk of two Eggs, a quarter
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:56968:73"/>of a pint of White-wine, an ounce of Oyl of St. <hi>Johns-wort,</hi> as much of the Oyl of Roſes, Plantain and Roſe-water, of each one ounce, bray them together, fold a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloath and dip it therein, warm it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a gentle Fire, and apply it to the Breaſt, and the pains of thoſe parts will be greatly eaſed.</p>
               <p>Preſent ſleep is not convenient, but above four hours after Delivery ſhe may take Broth, Caudle, or what other liquid mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is nouriſhing, and afterward if ſhe be diſpoſed to ſleep, it may be ſafely permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And this is as much, in caſe of a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Birth, as ought immediately to be done.</p>
               <p>In caſe of Extremity, or an unnatural Birth, theſe Rules ought to be obſerved: In the firſt place, let the Woman keep a temperate Diet, by no means overcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf after ſo demonſtrate an Evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; and to ſay true, her Diet muſt be equal to that of wounded perſons, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ruled, or giving Credit to unskilful Nurſes, who admoniſh them to feed luſty, the better to repair the loſs of Blood, for that Blood is not for the moſt part pure, but ſuch as has been detained in the Veſſels or Membranes, better avoided for the health of the Woman than kept, unleſs there happen an extraordinary Flux of Blood;
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:56968:73"/>for if her nouriſhment be over great, it will indanger her falling into a Feaver, nay more, it will increaſe the Milk to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity, which Curdling often times turns to Apoſtumes, wherefore it is requiſite for the firſt five days eſpecially, that ſhe take moderately Ponado broath, Poach'd Eggs, Gelly of Chickens or Calves feet, French Barley-broath, each day ſomewhat increaſing her allowance. If ſhe intend to be Nurſe to her Child, ſhe may take a little more than ordinary to increaſe the Milk by degrees, which muſt be of no continuance, but drawn off either by the Child or other wiſe. In this caſe likewiſe let her have Coriander or Fennel-Seed boyled in her Barley-broth: but by any means for the time ſpecified let her abſtain from Meat. If no Feaver trouble her, ſhe may drink now and then a ſmall quantity of White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine or Claret, as alſo Syrup of Maiden-Hair or other Syrup that is aſtringent, take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in a little Water well boyled: And after the ſuſpition of a Feaver, or fear of contraction of Humours in the breaſt, ſhe may be nouriſhed more plentifully with the broath of Pullets, Capons, Pidgeons, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Veal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which muſt not be till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eight days from the day of delivery is over, at what time the Womb, unleſs ſome
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:56968:74"/>accident hinder, has purged if ſelf; it will then likewiſe be expedient to give her cold Meats ſparingly, that ſo ſhe may be inabled to gather ſtrength, ſhe during the time reſting quiet and free from diſturbance, not ſleeping in the day time if ſhe can avoid it. If there happen any obſtruction in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuation of Excrement, a Glyſter may be adminiſtred to help the defect made after the manner following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Receipt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of both the Mallows and Pelletory of the Wall a handful of each, Cammomile and Mellilot Flowers, of each a handful, Anni-ſeeds and Fennel-ſeeds, of each two ounces, boyd them in the decoction of a Sheeps head, and take of this 3 quarters diſſolving in them of common Honey and courſe Suger, two ounces of each, and of new freſh Butter 3 ounces ſtrained well, and adminiſter it Glyſterwiſe, but if it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate not to your mind, then may you an ounce of Catholicon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:56968:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> What ought to be done to the Child when new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly born, with divers other matters relating thereto.</head>
               <p>THE Navel of the Child having been before recited, the Midwiſe muſt cleanſe the Infant, not only in the Face, but likewiſe the whole Body, anointing the Groyn, Hips, Buttocks, with Oyl of ſweet Almonds, or Oyl of Roſes, to make the Skin ſupple, and cloſe the Pores, thereby to exclude the penetration of the Air, and ſtrengthen the Members; nor would it be amiſs if ſhe ſhould take the decoction of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or Roſe-Cakes, and red Sage, decected in White Wine, and bath the Child there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, the decoction being blood-warm.</p>
               <p>The Infant being thus well anointed or ſuppled, and well dried, wrap it up warm and give it a ſpoonful of Sugar and Malla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, or a Sctuple of Mithridate or Venice Treacle, diſſolved in half a ſpoonful of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and after it a little Cardus-water, obſerving to bath or anoint it each morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as aforeſaid. If the Child have extream throws immediately afcer it comes into the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:56968:75"/>World, it muſt be rubed with the juice of Peletory or the Deeoction, into which freſh Butter is melted, or for wanting of that Spiriage Juice, with Hogs Greaſe applied to the Navel, with new layed Eggs, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or cemented with Nut-Oyl, laying them likewiſe to the Navel, or you may admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter a Clyſter made of Milk, the Yolk of an Egg, and a ſmall quantity of Sugar, which will undoubtedly eaſe the pain.</p>
               <p>Now ſome Children are born of evil conſtituted Parents, or are defective thro' the evil nouriſhment the Woman has unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly taken during her pregnancy, which occaſions the Child to be much afflicted with flegmatick Humours, to expel which you muſt lay the Child on one ſide, and then turn him to the other, for layed upon the back, it is ſubject to Suffocation or Strangling by the aſcent of the humour, the belly muſt above all things be kept ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, cauſing thereby the Infant to void the blood kept in the intrails from the time of its being in the Womb, by giving it a ſmall quantity of Suppoſitory of black Soap, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed with freſh Butter to take away the Acrimony of it, after which immediately let the Infant take a ſpoonful of Syrup of Violets, which will oblige the Flegm to paſs down; but if hear be defective, add to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:56968:75"/>the Syrup, half the quantity of Oyl of ſweet Almonds, bathng the Belly and Stomack of it, as often as it is undreſſed.</p>
               <p>If it happen that the Childs Cods be full of wind, the Child muſt be gently moved to and fro, and the Cods anointed with Oyl of Mirth, giving it the liquid of Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds decocted in ſmall drink, if they be ſwelled or extended with water, rub and chafe the Skin with freſh Butter, and the water will ſweat out. But what is more to be regarded than any other thing, is the chooſing of a good Nurſe, for upon that choice depends the thriving or not thriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Child, and in ſuch caſes theſe things ought to be regarded, <hi>viz.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that ſhe be not dull ſighted, ſquint-Eyed, or have down caſt looks; that ſhe be not conſumptive or ſubject to Fits, that her breath is pure, that ſo no noiſome va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour be conveyed to the Lungs of the Child, that ſhe be not infected with bloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, boils, blaines, or that ſhe, or her Husband never were afflicted with the French diſeaſe, that ſhe be not given to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive drinking or Gluttony, nor in the leaſt ſubject to Epileſie or falling Evil. For the Nurſe being in a manner the ſecond Mother to the Child, it drawing from her good or evil humours, eſpecially care muſt
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:56968:76"/>therefore be taken that the Nurſe be good conditiored, moderate in meat and drink, wakeful and vipilant, not fretful nor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Paſſion; that her Milk be clean and ſweet, flowing ſufficiently, her Breaſts well fixed and large, not over fleſhy, nor ſhe over fat, and above all that ſhe be not too deſirous of carnal copulation, by which means the Milk will be rendred unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. Having thus far proceeded in theſe offairs, I ſhall through God's bleſing lay down divers neceſſary matters for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Childing Women and Infants, thereby to prevent the hazard and loſs, which two often happens in ſuch caſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> To know the exact time of Delivery, by ſigns that precedes it, and how to cauſe a Woman to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Birth.</head>
               <p>IN the buſineſs of Generation nothing is more to be regarded by the Woman, than the time of her Conception and quickning, that thereby ſhe may be enabled to be exact in the day of her delivery, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:56968:76"/>natural delivery be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g at the end of 9 months, eſpecially if at the tune or near it, the Woman is wont to have her natural Purgations, or that the time fall out with the full or new Moon: Nay though a day or two before or after, for theſe things to falling out, not only haſten but facilitate delivery; and the knowledge of this muſt extend to the Woman for many reaſons. Firſt that ſhe may prepare and diſpoſe her ſelf for ſo great a task. Secondly, For that at ſuch a time divers Maladies are incident to her, nor can their cauſe be penetrated into, unleſs thoſe things be well known, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now one thing neceeſſary the better to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the Woman to underſtand it, is the time of her natural Courſes, for in caſe ſhe have forgot, or by not rightly underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their natural <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fflux or is puzled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by reaſon of ſome unnatural retention or extraordinary evacution, ſhe may recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy her judgment by theſe directions, <hi>viz.</hi> From the age of 14 to 21 Women have their Courſes, according to the moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral courſes in the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Moon; from 21 to 30 in the firſt Quarter; from 30 to 37 or 38 in the fud Moon; and from that time to the time they ceaſe in the laſt Quarter.</p>
               <p>Beſide what is before mentioned, ſhe will be made ſenſible of the approaching timeby
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:56968:77"/>pain in her Groyn, Thighs, the ſmall of her Belly, the lower part of her Navel, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſwelling, and hardneſs in the ſaid places, ſhivering &amp; quaking throughout the Body as if poſſeſſed with an Ague, and ſuddainly after with fluſhing heat; Feeble, neſs and Laſſitude, ſmall Sweats on the Face, and fluſhings of the blood there, as her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy will be in a manner reſtleſs, ſhe ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Child, more down ward with more force than ordinary, and a bloody water will diſtil from the inferior parts, in caſe of theſe Prodromos, as many term them, ſhe may be aſſured her time is at hand, whenas ſhemuſt not delay ſending for her Midwife, whoſe office 'tis to order her to the beſt advantage, directions for which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given; for wonderful it is that Nature has ſo well ordered her works, that the Matrix opens not unleſs upon ſome Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Caſualty before the time prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not till then do theſe ſigns appear: But appearing they ought to be much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, if the Woman deſire her own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the preſervation of the Child.</p>
               <p>In caſe the Woman be ſubject to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage or to come before her time, let her take Mint, Roſes, Marjorum, of each a ſmall handful, Saffron and Musk, of each 3 grains, bruiſe them to gether, put them in
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:56968:77"/>a bag flat and hang it about the Womans Neck, ſo that it may reach the pit of her Stomach, and it will draw the Womb up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or keep it in its place that it ſhall not fall down, or give the Child occaſion to ſeek for untimely paſſage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Of the Waſhing of Woman after Delivery, with Directions how to make them.</head>
               <p>FOR the firſt Waſh take a good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of young Charvil, boil it in 2 pints of water, which having done, add to it a ſpoonful of Honey of Roſes, and let the Midwife uſe it at her diſcretion, and it will draw down the Purgations, heal and cleanſe the afflicted part. There are ſome that uſe Milk inſtead of Water, affirming that it greatly mittigates the pain: but by thoſe whom Experience has taught better it is rejected: this having been uſed eight days the ſecond waſh may be made.</p>
               <p>Take Province Roſes moiſt if you can, but if not, the dry Cakes, put them in a little linnen Bag, and boyl them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:56968:78"/>in half a pint of Water, and half a pint of White Wine, and uſe it as the former for other eight days, <hi>viz.</hi> The li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid part being well ſtraine.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt waſh muſt be made of the decoction of Province Roſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted in a pint of VVhite VVine, and a quarter of a Pint of Mirth-water, and uſed only four days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> An Aſtringent for Women when occaſion requires, as alſo Directions for a Cere-Chath, and how to cleanſe her before ſhe riſe.</head>
               <p>TO make an Aſtringent, take Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granets, Roach Allum and Galls of each 2 ounces, Knot Graſs a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, of Province Roſes four ounces, the Rinds of Caſſa and Pomgranets, each 3 ounces, of Scarlet-berries, of Spermaceti, one ounce. The waters of Roſes, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n, and Burnet, of each one ounceand a half, white VVine, and water of the Smiths Forge of each a quarter of a Pint, then take two
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:56968:78"/>little baggs about a quarter of a yard long, and half a quarter broad, boyl them in the Waters with the Drugs or Simples in them, and in a new glazed Pipkin, and uſe them ſucceſſively as occaſion requires.</p>
               <p>To make an exceeding convenient Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath, to eaſe the pain and reduce the Body into good temperament.</p>
               <p>Take Virgins wax 8 ounces, <hi>Spermaceti</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, well waſhed in Roſe and Plantane water, of each an ounce and a half, adding to them whilſt they are melting an ounce of white Lead of <hi>Venice</hi> pulverized, and having by the operation of the Fire well mixed them together, ſpread them Plaiſterwiſe upon a Cloath, fit to cover the Belly as far as it is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, ſome of this you may lay upon the Nipples, having firſt anointed them with Oyl of Acrons of <hi>Spermaceti,</hi> and it will allay the inflammation and much ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them.</p>
               <p>To cleanſe a VVoman before ſhe riſes. Take a conſiderable quantity of bitter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, peel them, bruiſe them well, and make them into a Paſt, with the Yolk of an Egg, and Powder of Griſe, put the Paſt into a bag of Shamy, and dip it in black Wine, tempering it well, and uſe it upon the place where the Sear-cloaths have been
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:56968:79"/>laid, and after that waſh the ſaid places with black Wine, wherein Orange flowers have been ſteeped, and it will cleanſe theſe parts to admiration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> How to expell the Chollick from Women in Child-Birth, and the violent Griping that attend the firſt Delivery.</head>
               <p>THeſe Pains frequently afflict the Woman no leſs than the pangs of her Labour, and are by the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant taken many times the one for the other, ſometimes again they joyn Forces, and happen at the ſame inſtant, which is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the crudy matter in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach contracted through indigeſtion, and whilſt ſuch a Pain laſts, the Woman ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth nothing towards her Travel, to expel the fits of the Chollick; therefore,</p>
               <p>Take two ounces of ſweet Almond Oyl, and an ounce of Cinnamon-water, with 3 or 4 drops of Spirit of Ginger, and let the Woman drink it off, and if this work not your deſire, make a Glyſter of Cammomile
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:56968:79"/>Baum leaves, Olive-Oyl, and new Milk, concocting the former in the latter, and having ſtrained it very well adminiſter it as 'tis uſual in ſuch caſes; nor are Fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations proper for diſpelling wind amiſs.</p>
               <p>If the pain prove, the griping or fretting of the Guts continuing long after Delivery, or if it happen upon the Courſes deſcending by reaſon of the ſmallneſs of the Veins, which convey the Blood into the Matrix, which often befalls Women lying in of their firſt Child: wherefore it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther convenient to uſe ſuch a Remedy at ſuch a time as may eradicate the cauſe for the future: and above all I recommend this moſt approved one, uſed with ſucceſs by many Noble Women.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recepe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the Root of great Camfory a dram, Nutmegs and Peach-Kernels of each two ſcruples, yellow Amber and Amber greaſe of the former a dram, and the latter a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, bruiſe them together, and give them the Woman as ſoon as ſhe is layed down, in two or three Spoonfuls of White-wine, but if it ſo happen that ſhe be feveriſh, then let it be in as much warm Broth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:56968:80"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> The approved Receipts for hindring the Monthly Flux in Women with Child; alſo to cauſe Women that are fearful and ſubject to Abortion to contain the Birth: Together with preparato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ointments, to be uſed before the time of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, and Directions for ſtaying or preventing Vomiting, much incident to Women with Child.</head>
               <p>TO hinder the Superfluity or Eflux, dangerous to VVomen far gone with Child,</p>
               <p>Take the Oyl of Roſes, Virgins-wax, juice of Male Knot-graſs, of each 3 ounces, Bolearmonick, Crocus Martis, of each ſix drams, melt them and bruiſe them till they become plyant, and capable of being ſpread Plaſter wiſe, and when the Flux deſcends lay it to her Loyns whilſt ſhe lies in the bed. Or to the ſame effect, you may take Crocus Martis a dram, Knot-graſs juice, 4 ounces, Roſe-water and Vinegar, of each one ounce, adding to them the white of an Egg, and apply them cold upon a Linnen Cloath to her Loins. IOf the VVoman be
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:56968:80"/>fearful of containing the Birth, and reject to Abortion.</p>
               <p>Take the Roots of Tormentile and Snake-weed, of each an ounce and a half, Joubertus, Aſtringent Powder, Mirtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, Pſida, Pomgraner Flowers, of each ſix drams, Dragons-blood, and Spong-Bedeguar of each half an ounce, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and Maſtick, of each 3 drams, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg and Cloves of each half a dram, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pich ſix ounces, Cinnamon a dram, Venice Turpentine waſhed in the juice of Shepheards purſe 2 ounces, of Ship Pitch 3 ounces, Virgin-wax two ounces, melt and well imbody them till they become pliable to be ſpread Plaiſter-wiſe, and apply the Plaiſter upon Leather to the Reins.</p>
               <p>To make an Oyntment exceeding uſeful before Delivery. Take the Oyls of white Lilly Roots and Cammomile, each 4 ounces new Hogs-Seam ſtrained and freſh Butter of each an ounce and a half, Muſcilage of the Seed of Fenegreck extracted in Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort-water 2 ounces, the Powder of round Billwort Roots and Saffron, of each two drams, Wax an ounce and a half, melt them over a gentle Fire, and having ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth the ſupliſt part, anoint and ſupple the Womans Thighs, Hips, and Matrix therewith.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:56968:81"/>
               <p>In caſe of Vomiting or Nauſeating, which too frequently befalls young Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Women.</p>
               <p>Take a Cere-cloath, ſprinkle it with Galbanum, Powder of Cloves and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ick, them covering it with linnen or ſilk in the form of a Stomacher, apply it to the Stomach, renewing it as the ſcent decays.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> A Pomatum for Midwives to anoint their hands with when they are about their Office, as alſo the Womb of the Woman to be Delivered: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Applications to ſtraighten and ſtrengthen the Womb after Delivery.</head>
               <p>AMongſt the many Excellent Poma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tums or Oyntments for Midwives Hands, and anointing the Womb or Child to render the Birth eaſie, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend this as chief, <hi>viz.</hi> Take of Hemp ſeed Oyl an ounce and a half, half an ounce of Caſtor Oyl, Galmoſchate half a ſcruple, of Laudanum a ſcruple, with a
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:56968:81"/>gentle fire make them into an Oyntment, and attribute it to the uſe beforementioned.</p>
               <p>To contract the Womb after Delivery. Take the Leaves of Startwort and Mirtle, of each 3 ounces, Green Medlars, Pruans, and wild Pears, of each 8 or 9 ounces, the Stomachs of 3 Cocks freſh killed and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken out; all which diſtill, and dipping Cotten into the water iſſuing from them, make it into the form of a Peſſary and put it into the Womb, where let it continue a conſiderable ſpace.</p>
               <p>To ſtrengthen the Womb, take of Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Violet flowers, each a handful, Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany of <hi>Creet</hi> an ounce, Wood Sorrel a handful, Honey of Roſes half an ounce, Maiden-Hair an ounce, boyl them in White-wine, and Inject the Liquid part in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Womb, the woman taking ſoon after it, this potion, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Fennel and Bugloſs Roots, with <hi>Cicora ana</hi> take two ounces, boy them in 24 ounces of White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine to the conſumption of two parts, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding afterward Fennel water, and Cicory water, of each 3 ounces, boyling them again till a 5th part of what remains be conſumed, and of this let her drink an ounce at a time, continuing ſo to do Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening for 10 days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:56968:82"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> To keep the Milk from Curdling in the Breaſt, or to dry it up, moſt approved Receipt; as alſo to increaſe Milk.</head>
               <p>IF the Milk be ſubject to Curd in the Breaſt, paſt doubt in will contract pains or diſorder there, as well as in the Child that draws it forth; wherefore to prevent it ſo doing.</p>
               <p>Take the Roots of Althea half a pound, boyl them in White-wine Vinegar, ſtrain them through a fine Seive, adding to the liquid part Bean flower one ounce, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Rue and dried Mint, of each a dram, Oyl of Maſtick two ounces, boyl them again till they come to the thickneſs or plyableneſs of an Oyntment.</p>
               <p>To dry up the Milk take Honey newly taken from the Bees, diſſolve it in water, and often waſh the Breaſts therewith, or take the Juice of Speremint and Shepherds Purſe, of each half an ounce, mix them and ſweeten them with a little of the aforeſaid Honey, and drink them in the morning with the Broth of a Hen or Chicken.</p>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:56968:82"/>
               <p>Or ſhe may take of the Oyl of Violets 3 ounces, the juice of Mint and Paiſley a like quantity, an ounce of white-wine Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, Roſe water two ounces, boyl them over a gentle fire to the conſumption of the juice, adding a little wax to make them into an Oyntment, and anoint the Breaſt therewith; or for want of theſe, take El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der tops, Sage and Mint, of all of them a handful, boil them in Spring water loft, and lay them to the Breaſt.</p>
               <p>If the Woman be ſcarce of Milk, and for the benefit of the Child, ſhe would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it; Let her take the Decoction of Fennel and bath her Breaſt therewith, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the juice of Oak-Apples, and at the ſame time take inwardly this following powder, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Anniſeeds, Fennel ſeeds, and Cummin ſeeds, of each 2 drams, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Ginger half an ounce, of both ſorts of Pepper two drams, of Coral a dram, of Chriſtal and Cinnamon each a dram, the Seed of Daucia a dram, Silver Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tanus one ounce and a half, Cardamons and long Pepper of each a dram and a half, of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelcos half an ounce; the Seeds of Seſamum one ounce, of White-poppy one ounce, mingle and dry them till they are all capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being beaten into a powder: one
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:56968:83"/>dram of which the Woman muſt take at a time, Morning and Evening, in a broth made of Red Colwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, anointing her Breaſt the mean time with an Oyntment made of Venice Turpentine, Vinegar of Roſes and Bees wax, of each an equal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> For a Pain in the Breaſt immediately upon Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, or the Fiſſure.</head>
               <p>TAke new Bees-wax, two ounces, Nut Oyl half an ounce, Rape ſeed Oyl, the like quantity as the latter, when melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wax, add the Oyls, &amp; temper them well together to the thickneſs of a ſtiff Oyntment or Salve, and ſpread them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a cloth fit to cover the Breaſt, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it with extraordinary ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>In caſe a Fiſſure happen in the Breaſt, take of the Powder of Gun-Arabick one ounce, Roſe-water and <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> of each an ounce, prepare them by beating them together till they are of an apt thickneſs, then ſeeth them over the Fire, and when cool, apply them Plaiſter-wiſe to the Fiſſure
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:56968:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>or for want of theſe, take Unguentum Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum, and anoint the place grieved, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying upon it a Poltiſs of Ground Juice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> The Cauſe of the Bellies ſwelling after Delivery, and how to prevent it, or Cure it if it happens.</head>
               <p>Certain it is, and Experience teachet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> often, that many Women have their bellies ſwelled after Delivery as much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as before, and this happens through too much neglected &amp; careleſneſs, in not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving regard to foment them, as alſo to apply things convenient to the privities, by which means polite windineſs and Vapours enter and contract in the hollow Concavities, Veins and Arteries, the latter of which they enter by inſenſible ways: Now to prevent it, take Origanum, Night ſhade and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, of each a ſcruple, Sagapenum a dram, mix them together and make them into 7 Pills, take them all at once, and after them drink to the quantity of a quarter of a pint of the water of white Lillies, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Flowers.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:56968:84"/>
               <p>In c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe it be already come, let her take half a pound of Spaniſh Figgs, the Meal of Barley and Beans fine ſifted, four ounces of each, two ounces, of well burnt Brick, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verized, Cyprus Nuts one ounce, boyl them in as much water of the Smiths Forge as will ſuffice to bring them to a thickneſs, then ſpread them upon a Linnen Cloath, and apply them to the Belly twice or thrice, and it will retire to its wonted ſmallneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> Of Inflammations in the Breaſt, and its Cures.</head>
               <p>THE Inflammation of the Breaſt, is no other than the hard ſwelling, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ompa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed with a ſhooting pain, as alſo a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ating and redneſs, and is moſtly cauſed by the abundance of Blood, drawn or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wing to the Breaſt, and ſometimes but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely it is occaſioned by the ſuppreſſion of the courſes the Hemorrhoids or ſome bruiſe received by blow or the like and is known by a certain redneſs and burning heat,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:56968:84"/>cauſing the whole body to be feaveriſh and out of order. To cure it then, firſt let the Dyet be comforting, moiſtening, and of good nouriſhment, as the broth of Pullets, Capons, Cocks, Chickens, Veal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein Indive, Borrage, Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſlain or Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice has been boyled, and if ſhe can get it, let the Woman drink the juice of Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, but for want of that Barley-water, wherein Anniſeeds have been boyled, but let her refrain drinking of Wine, and ſtrong Liquors, as likewiſe hot Spices, and if ſhe find any obſtruction in her excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Evacuation, let her take a ſoftning or mollifying Glyſter, and ſleep at ſeaſonable times as much as ſhecan. Another way to remedy it is by diverting the Humours, which may be done by rubbing the body in all the adjacent places, letting Blood in the Foot, Scarification in the Legs, or Viſica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores applyed in thoſe places, eſpecially if the Courſes, are ſtopped, or ready to come down, if not, it is requiſite to bleed in the Arm.</p>
               <p>But if what has been mentioned, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd not to remove the Humours, make a Cataplaſm of the Leaves of Mellilot, and Nightſhade, each half a handful, and when boyled in Spring-water add to them Bean Meal 2 ounces, Oyl of ſweet Almonds and
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:56968:85"/>Oatmeal of each an ounce, and apply them to the Breaſt, obſerving ſo to do before the Breaſt be extraordinarily inflamed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIV.</hi> A Tumour in the Breaſt, its Cauſe and Cure.</head>
               <p>OF Tumours there are ſeveral ſorts, but firſt of the Flagitious Tumour, the cauſe of which proceeds from a thick and unnatural Vapour ariſing from the Menſtrual blood, which is retained or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in the Matrix, and that again is occaſioned by the ſuppreſſions of the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or when Nature is defective in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging them into their proper place, and due time, as alſo from corruption of humours, whereby are ingendered evil Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, and there paſſing by inſenſible ways, cauſes the Breaſt to ſwel or diſtend as if it were a true ſwelling, and is known by a ſhooting pain, and diſorder of the Heart, by reaſon of the wind that oppreſſes it; the left Breaſt being for the moſt part more ſwelled than the right, Communicating pains to the Arms and Shoulders, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:56968:85"/>the Ribs on the ſame ſide, the Breaſt being white and ſhining, ſounding like a Drum if touched gently, and ſwelled in all parts alike. To cure this, as alſo the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery Tumour, you muſt order the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to obſerve a moderation in diet, that thereby Crudities may be avoided, and all ſuch things as contract windy or valery hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in the Veins, ſuffering her to drink water wherein Cinnamon and Anniſeeds have been boyled, as alſo the Rind of Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, and then let her obſerve to take ſuch things as are proper to provoke the courſes, in doing which, ſhe will find the humours abate: then let her take Celondine, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, Groundſil &amp; Ground-juice, ſtamp them and boyl them in White-wine, and in ſo doing you will eaſe the pain, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Breaſt. As for Diſeaſes and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents incident to young Children, there are but fe VVomen of any experience but are skilful in curing and ordering them; wherefore, for brevities ſake, I ſhall paſs them over, and proceed to Anatomiſe the Inſtrument of Mans Generation, that one thing remaining neceſſary in this Treatiſe; as alſo to inſtance what Men nad Women ought to marry, that their Iſſue may be Fair, Healthful, and Proſperous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:56968:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> The Anatomy of the Inſtrument of Man's Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</head>
               <p>THE Yard of Man is an official Member, and the Tiller of Mans Generation, compound, and made of Skin, Brawns, Tendones, Veins, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ries, Sinews, and great Lygaments: And it hath in it two paſſages, or principal iſſues, one for the Sperm, and another for the Urine. And as the Philoſophers ſay, the quantity of a common Yard, is Eight or Nine Inches, with meaſurable bigneſs, proportioned to the quantity of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix.</p>
               <p>This Member hath (as <hi>Avicen</hi> ſaith) three holes, through one paſſeth inſenſible politions and wind, that cauſeth the Yard to riſe: the other two holes is declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Alſo the Yard hath a Skin, and about the head thereof it is double, and that Men call <hi>Praeputium,</hi> and this Skin is moveable, for through his conſecration the Spermatick matter is the better and ſooner gathered together, and ſooner caſt forth
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:56968:86"/>from the Teſticles: For by him is had the moſt delectation in the doing. And the foremoſt part of the head of the Yard before, is made of a brawny fleſh, the which if it be once loſt, it can never be reſtored again, but it may be well skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cods is a compounded Member, and an official, and though it be counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Generative Members, yet it is called a principal Member, becauſe of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. This Purſe was ordained for the cuſtody and comfort of the Teſticles and other Spermatick Veſſels: And it is alſo made of two parts, of the inner and of the outer.</p>
               <p>The outer is compound and made of Skin, and Lazartus, Longitudinal and Tranſverſal, in like manner as the <hi>Myrac.</hi> The inner part of the Cods is of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>Syfac,</hi> and are in ſimilitude as two Pockets drawn together by themſelves, and they differ not from the <hi>Syfac:</hi> And there be two, becauſe if there fall any hurt to the one, the other ſhould ſerve. The Teſticles or Stones be two made of Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous fleſh, or Curnelly fleſh. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, throug the <hi>Didimus</hi> cometh the Teſticles from the Brain, Sinews, and from the Heart, Arteries, and from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:56968:87"/>Veins, bringing unto them both feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtirring, Life and Spirit, and Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimental Blood, and the moſt pureſt blood of all other Members of the Body, whereof is made the Sperme by the labour of the Teſticles, the which is put forth in due time.</p>
               <p>The Groyns be known: They be the empty Junctures, or purging place unto the Liver, and they have Curnelly fleſh in the plying or bowing of the Thighs. The Hips have great brawny fleſh on them, and from thence deſcend downwards, Brawns, Cords, and Ligaments, moving and binding together the Thighs, with the Haunches themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVI.</hi> What Women ought to Marry, with what Men, that they may have Children.</head>
               <p>IN reſpect of Married Women that prove Childleſs, <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> adviſeth this Experiment to be tried, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the defect be on the Womans part, or on her Husbands, which is to make her
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:56968:87"/>ſuffumigations with Incenſe or Storax, with a Garment cloſe wrapped about her, which may hang down on the ground, in ſuch ſort that no Vapor or Fume may iſſue out; and if within a while after ſhe feel the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Incenſe in her Mouth, ſhe may conclude that the Barrenneſs comes not through her own defect, but through her Husbands, foraſmuch as the Fumes found the Paſſages open, whereby it pierced up to the Noſtrils: But although this proof perform that effect which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of, namely, the piercing up to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner part of the Mouth, yet this is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Argument of the Husbands Barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor of the Fruitfulneſs of the Wife; ſince want of Children may ariſe through an unapt diſpoſition in them both, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Correſpondency of Qualities; for it hath oftentimes happened that a Man who could not have Children by one Wife hath had them by another: the like alſo hath befallen Woman. What the Correſpondency ſhould be which the Man and Wife ought to bear each to other, is expreſſed by <hi>Hipprcrates</hi> in theſe Words, If the hot anſwer not the cold, and the dry the moiſt, with meaſure and quantity, that is, if there meet not in the Womb two Seeds, the one hot, the other cold, the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:56968:88"/>one dry, the other moiſt, extended in equal degree, there can be no Generation; for ſo marvellous a work as the Formation of Man could not be peform'd without a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable commixture of Seed, and the Womans were both of the ſame tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. To exemplifie what I have ſaid, it is to be concluded, that a Woman who is wily, ill condition'd, ſhrill-voiced, lean, ſwarthy coloured, and deformed, (which are the ſigns of cold and moiſt in the firſt degree) may conceive by a Man who is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, good natured, ſweet voyc'd, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent having little Hair, a well coloured Face, and a handſome Body, which are the ſigns of hot and dry in the firſt degree, in regard ſhe retaineth a mean in all thoſe ſigns above-mentioned, is moſt like to be Fruitful, becauſe ſhe comes neareſt in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to Men of each ſeveral tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But from the firſt of theſe Unions, or conjoyning of Man and Woman, are moſt likely to iſſue the wiſeſt Childen, becauſe the dryneſs of the Mother correcteth and amendeth the defect of the Father. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, it is requiſite that Woman be dried by a mature Age, and not marry over young; for from thence it comes to paſs, moſt commonly, that Children prove ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and indued with little wit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:56968:88"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> A Word of Advice to both Sexes in the time of Copulation.</head>
               <p>WHen the Husband cometh into hi Wives Chamber, he muſt enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her with all kind of dalliance, wanton behaviour, and allurements to Venery but if he perceive her to be ſlow and more cold, he muſt cheriſh, embrace, and tickle her, and ſhall not abruptly, the Nerves being ſuddenly diſtended, break into the Field of Nature, but rather ſhall creep in by little and little, intermixing more wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Kiſſes with wanton Words and Speech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, handling her Secret Parts and Dugs, that ſhe may take fire and be inflamed to Venery, for ſo at length the Womb will ſtrive and wax fervent with a deſire of caſting forth its own Seed, and receiving the Mans Seed to be mixed together there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. But if all theſe things will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to inflame the Woman, for Women for the moſt part are more ſlow and ſlack unto the expulſion or yielding forth of their Seed, it ſhall be neceſſary firſt to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment her Secret Parts with the Decoction of hot Herbs made with Muſcadine, or
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:56968:89"/>boyled in any other good Wine, and to put a little Musk or Civet into the Neck or Mouth of the Womb, and when ſhe ſhall perceive the Flu of her Seed to approach, by reaſon of the tickling pleaſure, ſhe muſt advertiſe her Husband thereof, that at the very inſtant, time, or moment, he may alſo yield forth his Seed, that by the concourſe or meeting of the Seeds, Conception may be made, and ſo at length a Child formed and born. And that it may have better Succeſs, the Husband muſt not preſently ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate himſelf from his Wifes Embraces, leſt the Air ſtrike into the open Womb, and ſo corrupt the Seeds before they are perfectly mixed together: when the Man departs, let the Woman lye ſtill in quiet, laying her Legs or her Thighs a-croſs one upon another, and raiſing them up a little leſt that by motion or downward ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Seed ſhould be ſhed or ſpilt; which is the cauſe why ſhe ought at that time not to talk, eſpecially chiding, nor to Cough or Sneeſe, but to give her ſelf to reſt and quietneſs, if it be poſſible.</p>
               <p>Thus, Reader, have I finiſhed the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Myſtery of Generation, as I hope, to the Satisfaction of all Modeſt and Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="collection_of_illustrations_with_descriptions">
            <pb facs="tcp:56968:89"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56968:90"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56968:90"/>
            <div type="illustration">
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Stecquer</hi> a Village of <hi>Saxony,</hi> they ſay, a Monſter was born, with four Feet, Eyes, Mouth, and Noſe like a Calf, with a round and red Excreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of Fleſh on the Forchead, and alſo a piece of Fleſh like a Hood hung from his Neck upon his back, and it was deform'd with its Thighs, torn and cut.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustration">
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:91"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parrey</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1573. he ſaw at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Church in <hi>Paris,</hi> a Boy Nine Years old, born in the Village <hi>Parpavilla,</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Guiſe;</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Name was <hi>Peter Renard,</hi> and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Marquete:</hi> He ahd but two Fingers on his right Hand, his Arm was well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned from the top of his Shoulder al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to his Wreſt, but from thence to his two Fingers ends it was very deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he wanted his Legs and Thighs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though from the right Buttock a certain unperfect Figure, having only four Toes, ſeemed to put it ſelf forth; from the midſt of the left buttock two Toes ſprung out, the one of which was not much unlike a Mans Yard, as you may ſee by the Figure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:91"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The Effigies of a monſtrous Child, by reaſon of the defect of the matter of Seed.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustration">
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:92"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1493. there was generated of a Woman and a Dogg, an iſſue, which from the Navel upwards perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled the ſhape of the Mother, but therehence downwards the Sire, that is, the Dogg. This Monſter was ſent to the Pope that then Reigned, as <hi>Volaterane</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: Alſo <hi>Cardane</hi> mentions it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have here given you the Figure thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:92"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The Effigies of a Monſter half Man and half Dogg.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustration">
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:93"/>
               <p>About the time that Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond raiſed up all <hi>Italy,</hi> and the greateſt part of Chriſtendome againſt <hi>Lewis</hi> the Twelfth, the King of <hi>France,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1512. (in which Year, upon <hi>Eaſter</hi>-day, near <hi>Ravenna</hi> was Fought that Mortal Battle, in which the Popes Forces were overthrown) a Monſter was Born in <hi>Ravenna,</hi> having a Horn upon the Crown of his Head, and beſides, two Wings, and one Foot alone, moſt like to Feet of Birds of Prey, and in the Knee thereof an Eye, the Privities of Male and Female, the reſt of the body like a Man, as you may ſee by this Figure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:93"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The Figure of a Winged Monſter.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustration">
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:94"/>
               <p>We have read in <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> that <hi>Perſna,</hi> Queen of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> by her Husband <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtes,</hi> being alſo an <hi>Aethiope,</hi> had a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a white Complexion, becauſe in the Embraces of her Husband, by which ſhe proved with Child, ſhe earneſtly fixed her eye and mind upon the Picture of the fair <hi>Andromeda</hi> ſtanding oppoſite to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Damaſcene</hi> reports, that he ſaw a Maid hairy like a Bear, which had that Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity by no other cauſe or occaſion than that her Mother earneſtly beheld, in the very inſtant of receiving and conceiving the Seed, the Image of St. <hi>John</hi> covered with a Camels skin, hanging upon the poſt of the bed.</p>
               <p>They ſay <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> by this Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Cauſes, freed a certain Noble Woman from ſuſpicion of Adultery, who being white her ſelf, and her Husband alſo white, brought forth a Child as black as an <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> becauſe in Copulation ſhe ſtrongly and continually had in her mind he Picture of the <hi>Aethiope.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:54"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Effigies of a Maid all Hairy, and an Infant that was black by the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of their Parents.</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="illustration">
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:95"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:56968:95"/>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jovianus Pontanus</hi> tells in the Year 1529. the ninth day of <hi>January,</hi> there was a Man-Child born in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> having four Arms and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Legs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
